<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Exact and faithful relation of the process pursued by Dame Margaret Areskine, Lady Castlehaven, relict of the decesed Sir James Foulis of Collingtoun, against Sir James Foulis now of Collingtoun, before the Lords of Council and Session with certain remarks upon the import and extent of protestations for remeed of law in general, and in particular upon the protestation or appeal offered by the Lady.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38878</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3598</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25698</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09070533</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09070533</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42385</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38878)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42385)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1283:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Exact and faithful relation of the process pursued by Dame Margaret Areskine, Lady Castlehaven, relict of the decesed Sir James Foulis of Collingtoun, against Sir James Foulis now of Collingtoun, before the Lords of Council and Session with certain remarks upon the import and extent of protestations for remeed of law in general, and in particular upon the protestation or appeal offered by the Lady.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[63] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at the Society of Stationers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1690]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Castlehaven, Margaret Erskine, --  Lady.</term>
               <term>Estates (Law) --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42385:1"/>
            <p>An Exact and Faithful RELATION OF THE PROCESS Purſued by Dame <hi>Margaret Areskine,</hi> Lady <hi>Caſtle-haven,</hi> Relict of the Deceaſed Sir <hi>James Foulis</hi> of <hi>Collingtoun;</hi> againſt Sir <hi>James Foulis</hi> now of <hi>Colling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toun;</hi> before the Lords of Council and Seſſion.</p>
            <p>WITH CERTAIN REMARKS Upon the Import and Extent of PROTESTATIONS For Remeed of LAW in General: And in Particular upon the <hi>Proteſtation</hi> or <hi>Appeal</hi> offered by the LADY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Printed at the Society of Stationers Printing-h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Harts-Cloſe,</hi> over-againſt the <hi>Trane Church</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:42385:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42385:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An Exact and Faithful RELATION OF THE PROCESS <hi>Purſued by Dame</hi> Margaret Arsekine, <hi>Lady</hi> Caſtle-haven, <hi>Relict of the Deceaſed Sir</hi> James Foulis <hi>of</hi> Collingtoun: <hi>Againſt Sir</hi> James Foulis <hi>now of</hi> Collingtoun; <hi>before the Lords of Council and Seſſion.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ame <hi>Margaret Areskine</hi> Lady <hi>Caſtlehaven.</hi> having ſuccumbed in a Proceſs purſued at her Inſtance, againſt Sir <hi>James Foulis</hi> of <hi>Collingtoun:</hi> She did Appeal and Proteſt for Remeed of Law, againſt the Interlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitor of the <hi>Lords of Seſſion:</hi> And in proſecution thereof, hath cauſed Print and publiſh a Petition to be preſented by her to the <hi>High Court of Parliament:</hi> In which ſhe doth not offer any diſtinct Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Proceſs, Debate, or Deciſion; but ſatisfies her ſelf with general groundleſs Aſſertions of the Juſtice of her Cauſe, and of the Iniquity of the Deciſion; whereby ſhe pretends, <hi>All Faith in Contracts is Violated, the Law which ought to protect Widows, wreſted to their Ruine: And fraud, and indirect Dealings, are not only encouraged, but own'd to be the deſign of Law:</hi> And which Deciſion, as it is pretended, <hi>Doth impugne Law, Equity, Juſtice, and Honeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:42385:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The <hi>Lady</hi> hath not thought fit to diſperſe or publiſh any part of the Proceſs, or Debate upon which the Interloquitor proceeded, For verifying of this great Charge againſt the <hi>Supreme Ordinary Court of Juſtice</hi> in the Nation, whom our Predeceſſors thought worthy to be the Depoſitars of the Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities of their own, and our, Properties and Poſſeſſions; but ſhe is pleaſed to lay the weight of all upon her own Aſſertion: And albeit bold Calumnies do oft-times leave ſome Impreſſion; yet this being a matter of the higheſt Concern, to the Intereſt and quiet of all, (not only thoſe who have Proceſs depending, but ſuch as may have them) It cannot be unacceptable, that <hi>Collingtoun</hi> ſhould publiſh to the World the whole Proceſs and Debate upon which the Interloquitor of the Lords of Seſſion proceeded; which indeed had been the proper part of the <hi>Lady,</hi> who makes the Complaint: By which means, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Lady</hi>'s Charge will be made good, or otherwayes the Juſtice of <hi>Collingtoun</hi>'s Defences, and the Integrity of the Lords will be Vindicate, and the Nation ſatisfied and quieted in the Evidence, that their Rights and Securities are ſafely lodged: And it is left to the Judgement of all unbyaſſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whether the former, or latter doth appear, upon peruſal and conſideration of the Proceſs, which followeth, with ſo great Candor and Favour to the <hi>Lady,</hi> that no part of her Claim, or any Evidence thereof produced is omitted; though ſeveral Decreets and Inſtructions produced for <hi>Collingtoun</hi> be forborn; leaſt the Proceſs might thereby appear too prolix.</p>
            <div type="contract">
               <head>Copy of the <hi>Lady</hi>'s Contract of Marriage.</head>
               <p>AT <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the firſt day of <hi>June</hi> one thouſand ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſixty one years: It is Appointed, Agreed, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted and Ended, betwixt the Honourable Parties following, to wit, <hi>Sir</hi> James Foulis <hi>of</hi> Collingtoun <hi>Knight, one of the Senators of the Colledge of Juſtice,</hi> on the one part: And <hi>Dame</hi> Margaret Areskine, <hi>Relict of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mwhile Sir</hi> Joh. M<hi rend="sup">c</hi>ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ȝie <hi>of</hi> Tarbat, on the other part; in Manner, Form, and Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb facs="tcp:42385:3"/>following: That is to ſay, the foreſaids Parties Binds and Obliges them to Solemnizat and Accompliſh the Holy Band of Marriage each of them with the other in face of Holy Kirk, with all Solemnities requiſite; betwixt the date hereof, and the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> next to come but longer delay. <hi>In Contemplation</hi> of the which Marriage, the ſaid Sir <hi>James Foulis</hi> Binds and Obliges him, to Renounce, Quite-claim and Over-give: Likeas, he by thir Preſents, Renounces, Quite-claims and Over-gives, all Right, Tittle and Intereſt, which he <hi>jure mariti</hi> can have claim or pretend, in and to the ſaid Dame <hi>Margaret</hi> her Conjunct-Fee, and Liferent-Lands, Teynds, and others belonging to her, wherever the ſamen lye within this Kingdom, declaring the generality of this preſent Renounciation to be as ſufficient, as if the ſaid haill Conjunct-Fee, or Liferent-Lands, Teynds, and others were inſert and ſet down here intill: Renouncing all Benefit of the Law, or other Benefit whatſoever, either competent, or that may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſs to him by this Contract, or by the ſubſequent Marriage, or by any manner of way whatſoever, to her ſaids Conjunct-Fee, or Liferent-Lands, or any part thereof, for now and ever; in Favours of her ſelf to be uſed and diſpoſed of at her plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. And by thir Preſents, doth take his hazard of what he may have otherwayes by the ſaid Dame <hi>Margaret. And farder, The ſaid Sir</hi> James Foulis <hi>by thir Preſents, Binds and Obliges him, his Heirs, Executors and Succeſſors, That in caſe it ſhall happen him at any time, during the Marriage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him and the ſaid Dame</hi> Margaret, <hi>to Conqueſce and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire any ſums of Money, Lands, or Heretages; or to Receive payment of Sums of Money due to him, in that caſe to Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy the ſamen, And take the Rights and Securities thereof in Favours of himſelf, and the ſaid Dame Margaret the long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Liver of them two, in Conjunct-fee and Life rent; and to the Heirs-male to be Procreat betwixt them; Whilks failing, to the ſaid Sir</hi> James <hi>his other Heirs, who are appointed to ſucceed him in his other Lands and Heretages.</hi> And in caſe their ſhall be no Heirs Male, but Female; The ſaid Sir <hi>James</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42385:4"/>Binds and Obliges him and his forſaids, to provide them to the half of the ſaid Conqueſt; and the other half thereof to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and belong to the ſaid Sir <hi>James</hi> his other Heirs foreſaids. <hi>Which</hi> Proviſion above-written, the ſaid Dame <hi>Margaret</hi> accepts, likeas it is hereby declared, That the ſamen is granted and provided to her, ard Heirs foreſaids to be Procreat of the ſaid Marriage, in full contentation and ſatisfaction of all other Conjunct-Fee, Terce, Third, Right of Moveables, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retage, or any other Right whatſoever; except allennarly the Mannor, Place, and Dwelling-houſe of <hi>Collingtoun,</hi> and Yairds thereof, which are hereby appointed and allotted to the ſaid Dame <hi>Margaret</hi> for a Dwelling-houſe during her Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time. Providing always ſhe ſufficiently Maintain and Uphold the ſaid Houſe, and Houſes in as good Condition, as they ſhall be in, at the time of the ſaid Sir <hi>James</hi> his Deceaſe: And that ſhe ſhall not Directly, or Indirectly be her ſelf, or any others in her Name, or at her Direction, cut, or deſtroy any manner of growing Trees, or Planting about the ſaid Houſe or Yairds, or within any part of the Bounds of <hi>Collingtoun,</hi> for no pretext nor uſe whatſoever. And for the more Security, both the ſaids Parties are content and conſent that thir Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents be inſert and Regiſtrat in the Books of Council and Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or in the Court Books of any other competent Judge within this Kingdom; to have the ſtrength of an Decreet of any of the ſaids Judges, and their Authority Interponed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, that executorials of Horning upon an ſimple Charge of ten dayes and others competent, may be direct hereupon: And for that effect Conſtituts — Their Procurators, <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitten de Rato,</hi> &amp;c. In witneſs whereof, both the ſaids parties have Subſcribed thir preſents, (which are written be <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Keith,</hi> Servitor to Mr. <hi>Andrew Gilmour</hi> Advocate) day, place and year of God above written. Before thir Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, Sir <hi>William Murray</hi> of <hi>Dreghorne</hi> Maſter of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Works, and Sir <hi>John Foulis</hi> of <hi>Ravelſtone</hi> Younger. Sic Subſcribitur <hi>Ja. Foulis, M. Areskine, W. Moray</hi> witneſs, <hi>Jo. Foulis</hi> witneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:42385:4"/>
               <head>Double of the Summonds, Dame <hi>Margaret Areskine</hi> againſt Sir <hi>James Foulis</hi> of <hi>Collingtoun.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>JAmes,</hi> &amp;c. Forſuameikle as it is humbly meaned and ſhowen to us by our Lovet Dame <hi>Margaret Areskine</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lict of the Deceaſed Sir <hi>James Foulis</hi> of <hi>Collingtoun,</hi> late <hi>Juſtice Clerk, and one of the Senators of our Colledge of Juſtice.</hi> That where the ſaid perſuer therein deſigned Relict of the Deceaſed Sir <hi>John Mekenȝie</hi> of <hi>Tarbat</hi> be her Letters of Aſſignation and Diſpoſition Subſcribed with her Hand, of the date the laſt day of <hi>May</hi> 1661. years (for the Cauſes therein ſpecified) Sold, Aſſigned, Transferred and Diſponed from her, her Airs and Aſſigneys; to and in Favours of Mr. <hi>Adam Cunningham</hi> of <hi>Woodhall</hi> his Airs and Aſſignes whatſomever: <hi>All and hail</hi> her Life-rent Right of the Lands, Teynds and others after ſpecified, <hi>to wit,</hi> Of all and ſundry the Lands and Barrony of <hi>Innerteil,</hi> therein comprehending the <hi>Maynes</hi> of <hi>Innerteil,</hi> Mannor, Place, Houſes, Biggings, Yards, Orchards, Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat and pertinents thereof, <hi>Bridge,</hi> and Lands of <hi>Bridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> called the Village of St. <hi>Katherines,</hi> with the Chapel of St. <hi>Katherines,</hi> and Gift of Chapellanry of the ſamen, with the Houſes about the ſaid Chapel, and ſpecial Pendicle of the ſaids Lands, called St. <hi>Germans-Aiker;</hi> together with all Edifices, Yards, Tofts, Crofts, Coals, Coalheughs, Lyme and Lyme-quarrel, with the <hi>Mylne, Mylne-lands</hi> and Multurs of the ſamen, Salmond Fiſhing, and other Fiſhings, as well in Salt as Freſh Waters, annexis, connexis, parts, pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicles and pertinents whatſomever of all and ſundry the Lands and Barrony of <hi>Innerteil,</hi> lyand within the Sheriffdom of <hi>Fife</hi> as principal: And alſo of all and ſundry the Lands and Barrony of <hi>Glengarnock,</hi> comprehending the ſpecial and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Lands therein mentioned; and that in ſpecial Warrandice and Security of the ſaids Lands and Barony of <hi>Innerteil:</hi> And ſick like of <hi>all and hail</hi> the half Lands of over and nether <hi>Tyries;</hi> with Houſes, Biggings and Pertinents thereof, lyand within the:
<pb facs="tcp:42385:5"/>Regality of <hi>Dalkeith,</hi> Conſtabulary of <hi>Kinghorne</hi> and She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffdom of <hi>Fife,</hi> wherein the ſaid Dame <hi>Margaret Areskine</hi> perſuer was infeſt upon the 25 day of <hi>February</hi> 1645. Years; and ſiclike <hi>of all and ſundry</hi> the Teynd Shaves of <hi>all and hail</hi> the ſaids lands of <hi>Innerteil</hi> and <hi>Bridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> of <hi>Innerteil</hi> with all and ſundry parts, pendicles and pertinents thereof, and <hi>of all and ſundry</hi> the teynd ſheaves of <hi>all and haill</hi> the lands of <hi>Sea-field</hi> and the ſaids half lands of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> with their parts, pendicles, and pertinents above mentioned; And alſe <hi>of all and haill</hi> the teynd ſheaves of all and ſundry the lands of <hi>Balbartuon,</hi> mylnelands thereof and pertinents of the ſamen; and <hi>of all and ſundry</hi> the teynd ſheaves of <hi>all and haill</hi> the lands of <hi>Morislands</hi> with their pertinents all lying in the ſaid <hi>Parochin of eaſter Kinghorn, and ſhirefdome of Fife,</hi> and pertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the parſonage of the ſaid paroch Kirk, ſpecified and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in an Tack ſet be the Earle of <hi>Kinghorn</hi> to the deceaſt Sir, <hi>George Areskin</hi> then of <hi>Innerteil,</hi> and Dame <hi>Iſabel Bruce</hi> his Spouſe, &amp; aſſigned be them to the ſaid perſuer, together with the Fruits, Rents, Emoluments &amp; duties of the ſamen, Males, Ferms Kaynes, Cuſtoms, Caſualities Tack-duties and other ſervices and duties due and payable to the ſaid Dame <hi>Margaret Areskin</hi> for the ſaids Lands, Stock and Teynd thereof, and that during the ſecond Marriage. With power to him to Call Follow and Purſue therefore, Decreets and Sentences thereupon to recover, and to remove and output Tennents therintil and to do all other things requiſit annent the premiſſes; And thereby made and conſtitute the ſaid Mr. <hi>Adam Cunnigham</hi> her Ceſſioner and Aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in and to the foreſaids Rights and Diſpoſition of the ſamen: As the ſaid Aſſignation and Diſpoſition of the date fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid at more length proports Like as the ſaid Mr, <hi>Adam Cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> be his letters of Tranſlation of the dait the laſt day of <hi>May</hi> 1661 years for the cauſes therein expreſt) ſold, aſſigned, transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and diſponed to and in favors of the deceaſt Mr. <hi>Alex. Foulis</hi> of <hi>Ratho,</hi> the foreſaid Right and Diſpoſition of the Conjunct-Fee Lands, Teynds and others above wirttten made and granted be the ſaid perſuer to him in manner above expreſt; and
<pb facs="tcp:42385:5"/>ſurrogate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Tranſlation and Diſpoſition of the date foreſaid, at more length bears, <hi>And ſicklike,</hi> the ſaid Deceaſed Mr. <hi>Alexander Foulis</hi> of <hi>Ratho</hi> be his back-band ſubſcribed with his Hand of the date, the laſt day of <hi>May</hi> 1661 years (Narrating the foreſaid Aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation granted be the ſaid perſuer to the ſaid Mr. <hi>Adam Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningham</hi> and the foreſaid Tranſlation granted be the ſaid Mr. <hi>Adam</hi> to the ſaid Deceaſed Mr. <hi>Alexander Foulis</hi>) Mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the ſaid <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mwhile</hi> Mr. <hi>Alexander Foulis,</hi> taking to conſideration, that the ſaid Aſſignation, Tranſlation and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and Right of Life-rent foreſaid therein mentioned, was made and granted to him, no ways for his own uſe, Utilitie, and Benefit, but that the ſamen was only made uſe of in his Name, and the ſame borrowed thereto, for the uſe, Utilitie, and Profit of the ſaid Deceaſed Sir <hi>James Foulis</hi> of <hi>Collingtoun,</hi> and the ſaid perſuer his Spouſe during all the dayes of their Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time joyntly for the Intertainment and Aliment of their Family allennerly, and upon thir expreſs Terms, that the ſamen, or any parts thereof ſhould not be lyable to be affected directly or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly with the burding of the ſaids perſons their Debts, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone, preſent, or to come; and that none of their Creditors ſhould have any Action againſt the ſamen, or any part thereof: Therefore he band and obleiſt him to denude himſelf of the ſaid Life-rent Right, and of all Right, Tittle and Intereſt which he either had, or could have, claim or pretend thereto, or any part thereof: <hi>Likeas,</hi> the ſaid Deceaſed Mr. <hi>Alexander Foulis</hi> be the Tenor of the ſaid Band <hi>per verba de eodem,</hi> did denude himſelf and his Airs therein mentionat thereof; and Band and Obleiſt him and his foreſaids to Diſpone, likeas he thereby Aſſigned. Transferred and Diſponed the ſaid Life-rent Right, withall Right, Title and Intereſt, Claim of Right, or Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion which he had, or could pretend thereto, To and in Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of the ſaid deceaſt Sir <hi>James,</hi> and the ſaid perſuer in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner foreſaid, with Power to them to uſe and Diſpone thereupon at their pleaſure; for the uſe and effect foreſaid allennerly, and upon the expreſs Proviſions and Conditions above writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,
<pb facs="tcp:42385:6"/>and no other wayes; And in caſe it ſhould happen the ſaid Perſeuer to ſurvive the ſaid Deceaſed Sir <hi>James Foulis</hi> her Husband. It is thereby declared, That in that Caſe the foreſaid Right of Life-rent abovewritten was only in truſt and to her own proper uſe and behove; like as in the forſaid caſe the ſaid deceaſed Mr. <hi>Alexander Foulis</hi> band and obleiſt him and his forſaids, to transfer the premiſſes in favours of the ſaid per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſewar, like as he thereby transferred the ſamen in her Favours: As the ſaid back band of the date forſaid, inſert and regiſtrated in the Books of our Council and Seſſion upon the 17 of <hi>Janua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> 1667 years more fully proports. <hi>And in like manner</hi> be Contract of Marriage paſt betwixt the ſaid deceaſed Sir <hi>James Foulis</hi> of <hi>Collingtoun,</hi> and the ſaid perſwar on the ane and other partes, of the Date, the firſt day of <hi>June</hi> and year of God fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid 1661 years, in contemplation of the Marriage then Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted and thereafter ſolemnized, the ſaid deceaſed Sir. <hi>James Foulis</hi> band and obleiſt him, to Renounce, Quite-claim and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give, like as he thereby renounced quite claimed and overgave, all Right Title and Intereſt which he <hi>Jure mariti</hi> could have claime or pretend in and to the ſaid perſuer her conjunct-fie or lyfe-rent Lands, Teynds and others belonging to her wherever the ſamen lye within this our Kingdom, Renouncing thereby all Benefit of the Law, or other Benefit whatſomever whilks might accrew to him by the ſaid Contract or any manner of way whatſomever, to her ſaid conjunct fie or Liferent Lands or any part thereof for ever, In Favours of the ſaid perſuer, to be uſed and diſpoſed of at her pleaſure, and did thereby take his hazard of what he might have otherwayes by the ſaid perſuar, And further the ſaid deceaſed Sir <hi>James boulis</hi> did thereby bind and obleis him his airs executors and ſucceſſors, that in caſe it ſhould happen him at any time during the Marriage betwixt him and the ſaid perſuer, To conqueis and acquire any ſumes of money, lands or heretages, or to receive payment of ſumes of money due to him, In that caſe, to imploy the ſame and take the rights and ſecurities thereof in favors of himſelf and the ſaid perſewar the longeſt liver of them two in conjunct-fie or lifrent,
<pb facs="tcp:42385:6"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſaid <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mwhile</hi> Sir <hi>James,</hi> his other Airs who are appointed to ſucceed him in his other Lands and Heretages: As the ſaid Contract of Marriage of the date foreſaid Inſert and Regiſtrat in the Books of Our Council and Seſſion upon the ſaid 17 day of <hi>January</hi> 1667. years likewayes more fully proports. <hi>And true it is,</hi> and of verity, that the ſaid <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mwhile</hi> Sir <hi>James Foulis</hi> the ſaid perſewers Husband during the time of the foreſaid Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage hes Conqueſt and Acquired, and hes received payment of ſums due to him, which will extend to the ſum of two hundreth and threeſcore thouſand Merks, which by the foreſaid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract he was obleiſt to imploy and ſecure upon Lands and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retages, and take the Rights and Securities thereof, in Favours of himſelf and the ſaid perſewer, the longeſt liver of them two: And by the foreſaid Back-band the Mailles and Duties of the ſaid Lyferent Lands, provided to the ſaid Perſewer in manner foreſaid, extending yearly to the number of thirty ſix Chalders of Victual, was to be Imployed for the Maintenance of the ſaid Deceaſt Sir <hi>James Foulis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and the ſaid perſewer their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily: Nevertheleſs the ſaid <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mwhile.</hi> Sir <hi>James Foulis</hi> hes not Imployed and Secured the ſaid ſum of two hundreth and threeſcore thouſand Merks Conqueſt and Acquired, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by him as ſaid is, and taken the Rights and Securities thereof in Favours of himſelf and the ſaid perſewer and the longeſt Liver of them two, in Conjunct-Fee and Lyfe-rent, as ſaid is; nor yet did he Imploy the ſaid threttie ſix Chalders of Victual for the Maintenance of his own and the ſaid perſewers Family, but did actually uplift and Intromet with twenty four Chalders of Victual of the ſaid 36 Chalders of Victual, for the particular years of God after ſpecified, of the quantities, quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and pryces after rehearſed, <hi>viz</hi> 22 Chalders of Bear, and two Chalders of Meal yearly out of the Lands and Barrony of <hi>Innerteil,</hi> and that for the Cropts and Years of God, 1661, 62, 63, 64, 65, 66, 67, 68, 69, 70, 71, 72, 73 74, 75, 76, 77, 78, 79, 80, 81, 82, 83, 84 85, 86, and 1687 years, each Boll of the ſaid Victual, Meal and Bear over head being worth ſix
<pb facs="tcp:42385:7"/>Pounds Money of this our Realm <hi>communibus annis</hi> of the years above mentioned, conform to the Current pryces of ſuch Victual grow and in that part of the Countrey. And that the ſaid perſewer, during the ſaid ſpace of twenty ſix years, did Maintain the ſaid Deceiſt Sir <hi>James Foulis</hi> his Family with all ſuitable Intertainment; and did pay the rent of his Lodging wherein he Dwelled during the ſaid ſpaces, and payed all Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants Fees. <hi>And albeit,</hi> Sir <hi>James Foulis</hi> now of <hi>Collingtoun</hi> eldeſt lawful Son, and appeirand Air to the ſaid, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mwhile</hi> Sir <hi>James Foulis</hi> his Father, and Executor nominate and confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him, at leaſt Succeſſor to him in his Lands and Heretages <hi>titulo lucrativo poſt Contractum debitum,</hi> and univerſal Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mettor with his moveable Airſhip Goods and Geir, and Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chiſt, ought and ſhould ſecure the ſaid perſewer in an Lyfe-rent Right during all the dayes of her Lyfe-time, of the ſaid Sum of two hundreth and threeſcore thouſand Merks Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queiſt, Acquired and received by his ſaid Father, as ſaid is; and to make payment to her of the ſaid 24 Chalders of Victual uplifted by his ſaid <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mwhile</hi> Father out of her ſaid Lyfe rent Lands; which ſhould have been applyed for the Maintenance of her Family as ſaid is: And that for the particular years of God and Cropts above expreſt, of the quantities, and qualities parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly above rehearſed, or liquidat pryces thereof above-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, extending to the ſum of <hi>fifty nine thoſand, nine hundreth and four Pounds Money</hi> foreſaid, after the Form and Tenor of the foreſaid Contract of Marriage and other Writs above dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in all points: Nevertheleſs he wrongouſly refuſes ſo to do without he be compelled. <hi>Our Will is herefore,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Given under our Signet at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> 
                     <date>the twenty day of <hi>February,</hi> and of our Reign the 4th. year.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:42385:7"/>
               <head>Information for Dame <hi>Margaret Areskine</hi> Lady <hi>Caſtle-haven, Againſt</hi> The Lord <hi>Collingtoun.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE deceiſt <hi>Lord Collingtoun</hi> being ingaged in debts above the value of his Eſtate, In the treatie of Marriage betwixt him and <hi>Dame Margaret Areskin,</hi> by the advice of Lawyers, there was threttie Six Chalders of victual of the Lady's joynture conveyed before the Marriage in the name of <hi>Ratho.</hi> for the mantenance of the Family; And in the contract of Mariage <hi>Collingtoun</hi> did renounce his <hi>jus mariti,</hi> that his Ladys Eſtate might not be ſubject to his Creditors; and their being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to which he ſhould provide her, all her intereſt in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract did depend upon this Clauſe, <q>
                     <hi>That incaſe he ſhall happen at any time during the Marriage to conqueſce and acquire, any ſums of money, Lands or Heretages, or to receive payment of ſums of money due to him, in that caſe to imploy the ſame, and take the Rights and Securities thereof in favours of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and the ſaid</hi> Dame Margaret Areskin <hi>and the longeſt liver of them two in conjunctfie,</hi>
                  </q> And for this hope of Conqueſce, my Lady renounced the terce of heretages and third of move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables, competent to her by Law.</p>
               <p>My Lady purſues this Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> as repreſenting his Father, for the lyfrent of the ſums conqueſt and received by his Father during the Marriage And condeſcends upon the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars ſums received by my <hi>Lord Collingtoun</hi> for 24 Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Victual of the Lady's Joynture lands yearly, (beſides what was Imployed for the uſe of the Family) and for Salla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Penſions, and otherwayes.</p>
               <p>It was alledged for the Defendar, 1. That it could not be ſubſumed that <hi>My Lord Collingtoun</hi> had aquired Lands or Heretages during the Marriage; and that ſums imployed for payment of Debts, or clearing a mans heretages from Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances, was never underſtood <hi>Conqueſce,</hi> but only an acceſſory Right to the Heretage. And therefore in the competition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb facs="tcp:42385:8"/>an <hi>Heire of Conqueſce,</hi> and an <hi>Heir of Line,</hi> where the Predeceſſor had a null defective Right, and thereafter had aquir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a valide and effectual Right to the ſame Lands, It was not found <hi>Conqueſt</hi> to belong to the <hi>Heire of Proviſion,</hi> but to belong to the <hi>General Heire,</hi> as acceſſory to the Heretage. 2. a <hi>Clauſe of Conqueſt,</hi> can never be underſtood to bind up the Fiar, or denude him of the Faculty and Capacity to imploy, or diſpoſe upon the <hi>Conqueſt</hi> at his pleaſure; and therefore <hi>Clauſes of Conqueſce</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports no more, but that ane <hi>Heire of Proviſion,</hi> or <hi>Relict</hi> ſhall ſucceed, or lyfrent, what Conqueſce remains undiſpoſed upon at the Fiars deceaſe, 3. The laſt clauſe <hi>(or if I ſhall happen to receive any Sums due to me)</hi> does relate to debts which was then due to <hi>Collingtoun,</hi> and particularly a ſum due by the Marqueſs of <hi>Huntly;</hi> and if that ſum ſhould be recovered, it was to be lifrented by my Lady. But the Clauſe cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended beyond ſums due to him at the Marriage, and all ſums that ſhould become due to him did fall under the former <hi>clauſes of Conqueſce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was replyed for my Lady, 1. The clauſe in her Favours, Is not only a <hi>Clauſe of Conqueſce,</hi> But to take off all debate, or Cavil that might ariſe anent the Interpretation of <hi>Conqueſce,</hi> this ſpecial Clauſe is ſubjoined, that whatever ſums my <hi>Lord Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingtoun</hi> ſhould receive, <hi>Eo ipſo,</hi> that he received the ſums, he became bound to imploy them in lyfrent to my Lady, and this by the advice of <hi>Lawyers,</hi> who could expect nothing from the <hi>Lord Collingtoun,</hi> but his Penſions and Sallaries from the King, to which he had great pretenſions; theſe ſums as ſoon as ever they came to be received, became ſubject to her Lyfrent; and therefore my Lady has it in her Option, either to inſiſt on the <hi>Clauſe of Conqueſce</hi> for all the ſums of mony that were imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the redeeming of the Eſtate of <hi>Collingtoun,</hi> or for the Lyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of the ſums Lybelled as he received them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Clauſes of Conqueſce,</hi> are moſt ordinary and known ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, and it were abſurd and againſt the common Faith of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts of Marriage (which of all others ought to be moſt Sacred) to render ſuch obligations Eluſorie, and at the arbitriment of the
<pb facs="tcp:42385:8"/>partie ingaged, and debitor in theſe obleiſments. And albeit <hi>Heirs of Proviſion or Conqueſce,</hi> as they are <hi>Creditors,</hi> ſo they do repreſent and ſucceed; and as they can have no Action againſt their Predeceſſor, ſo they are bound to have a regard; and the <hi>Law</hi> in ſome Caſes hath releived them from the ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their obleiſment in favours of their own Succeſſors, and hath allowed them a latitude to diſpoſe, or imploy their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt to all neceſſary and even rational uſes; But a Wife is meerly a <hi>Creditor,</hi> and therefore the obleiſment of <hi>Conqueſce</hi> in her favours, ought to be more ſtrictly and rigidly obſerved then to <hi>Heirs.</hi> And yet the <hi>Law</hi> nor <hi>practique</hi> did never relax any obleiſment of <hi>Conqueſce</hi> to tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> degree; that the debitor in the obleiſment might prejudge the obleiſment, and totally evacuat the ſame; and certainly it were a plain defrauding of this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiſment, If <hi>my Lord Colligtoun</hi> did imploy the conqueſt of this Marriage, to releive his Eſtate, of debts contracted in a former. And if this Doctrine hold, if their had been Heirs of this Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, they ſhould not have had a ſixpence, notwithſtanding they are provided out of the Conqueſce, which would looſe all the Faith and Security of Contracts.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whatever latitude the <hi>Lords</hi> may take, where a Wife is otherwayes provided, and hath only the Conqueſt as a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and acceſſory clauſe, yet where a wiſe gets nothing but the Conqueſce it were abſurd totally to fruſtrat and defraud Her.</p>
               <p n="4">4 In contemplation of this <hi>Conqueſce,</hi> the <hi>Lady</hi> did renounce a third of the Eſtate of <hi>Collingtoun,</hi> and it is inconſiſtent with the Reputation or Juſtice of the Seſſion to debar her from the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſce</hi> by ſuſtaining the imployment of the <hi>Conquest</hi> for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming of that heretage whereof ſhe had renounced her terce.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The other half of the Clauſe puts the debate of <hi>Conqueſce</hi> out of Doors, and founds the <hi>Ladies</hi> Right upon the preciſe receiving of mony. And whereas it is pretended that the Clauſe is only relative to ſums due at the Marriage, and not to ſums that ſhould become due during the Marriage,</p>
               <p>It is anſwered, 1. This is no diſtinct Clauſe, but a ſeparat view or part of the former, viz. <hi>And in caſe he ſhall happen at
<pb facs="tcp:42385:9"/>any time during the Marriage to conqueſce, and acquire ſums of Money, Lands, or Heretages, or to receive any ſums of money due to him</hi> viz <hi>During the Marriage,</hi> Which is underſtood to be repeated, as well at the laſt, as at the firſt part of the clauſe; And if it had been otherwayes deſigned, it had been eaſie to have Expreſt it thus <hi>(preſently belonging to him)</hi> And the word <hi>(due to him)</hi> was to exclude my Lady from any intereſt that ſhe might pretend to ſums borrowed and received by him. And it is evident that it is all but one Clauſe, becauſe the obleiſment to Imploy is ſubjoyned to both. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herefore the words <hi>(acquired during the Marriage)</hi> muſt be underſtood to be repeated in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the ſums received due to him, as well as the ſums, Lands, and Heretages, are to be imployed to my <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Lady</hi> in lyfrent and <hi>Children</hi> in fie. 2. In common Stile when men ſpeake of ſums belonging to them at the time, they doe not ſay <hi>(received,)</hi> but in caſe they ſhall uplift, or where the ſums are doubtful, incaſe they ſhall recover; and <hi>(Receive)</hi> is never uſed but either in relation to Donations, or where money is offered, and the parties required to receive their Money. 3. It cannot be condeſcended upon that any ſums of Money were due to <hi>Collingtoun,</hi> but an pretended Debt due by <hi>Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> which ſingle Debt could never anſwer the Clauſe <hi>(in caſe I ſhall receive ſums)</hi> And certainly if this Debt had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, it would have been expreſt; for where there is only one particular under conſideration, no body uſes to expreſs that ſingle thing under a generality, when there is nothing elſe can be included. 4. If this Clauſe had been meant of <hi>Huntley</hi>'s Debt, why was the Lyfe-rent only granted, in caſe the ſum were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, for a mans uplifting and recovering his own was never <hi>Conqueſce;</hi> and therefore if this Clauſe had been meant to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend no farther then Debts due to <hi>Collingtoun</hi> the time of the Marriage, the <hi>Lady</hi> would have been provided to the Lyfe-rent of all Debts due to him without that condition and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity <hi>(In caſe he ſhould receive them.)</hi> But the truth is, my Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> was a man of more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngenuity then to have ſham'd his <hi>Lady</hi> with mentioning this Debt, which neither is
<pb facs="tcp:42385:9"/>nor ever was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> is but of a few dayes before the Sentence againſt the Marqueſs of <hi>Argyle:</hi> And it was then perfectly underſtood, that <hi>Huntely</hi> was to be Donator to <hi>Argyles</hi> Forfeiture; in ſo far as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned <hi>Huntley</hi>'s Eſtate; ſo that this Debt was for ever ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded. But ſuppoſe there were no Forfeiture in the Caſe; the expyred Compryſings did abſolutely convey his Eſtate; and it was poſſeſſed be the Marqueſs of <hi>Argyle</hi> be vertue of theſe Compryſings, and not be the Forfeiture, for this Debt was never worth the regarding, much leſs to be the only ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the ſeparate Clauſe. 5. In this Senſe, the Clauſe had been ridiculous and of no Security to my <hi>Lady;</hi> for if her right to Lyfe-rent the ſums due to <hi>Collingtoun</hi> did depend upon his pleaſure in uplifting and recovering theſe ſums; then the obligment imports no more, then that my <hi>Lady</hi> ſhould Lyfe-rent what he pleaſed; for it could not be expected that he would prejudge his Heirs by uplifting ſums only to gratify his <hi>Lady</hi> with a Lyferent: And theſe abſurdities muſt convince, that this can never be the genuine meaning of the Clauſe; but the deſigne is plain, and the words are adapted to <hi>Penſions and Sallaries which he ſhould receive as due to him during the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage:</hi> And it is a general Rule in the Interpretation of all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts and Clauſes, <hi>That, that Senſe and Conſtruction ſhould be admitted, whereby the Clauſe ſhould not be ſuperfluous, redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, and ridiculous:</hi> And in this Caſe, the Clauſe muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther operate a Lyfe-rent of the ſums Conqueſt, or of all the ſums received; or elſe all the Proviſions in Favours of the <hi>Lady,</hi> for which ſhe renounced her Terce, and third part, was ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous and eluſory. 6. By the Clauſe in the Contract of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, my Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> being obliged to Imploy, <hi>All ſums of Money, Lands, or Heretages, that he ſhould happen to acquire, or ſums of Money due to him, whereof he ſhould receive payment during the Marriage:</hi> Albeit the <hi>Lady</hi> might juſtly crave the Lyferent of all the ſums of Money that can be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed my Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> received during the Marriage, which is the expreſs Terms in the Clauſe of the Contract, yet
<pb facs="tcp:42385:10"/>ſhe declares that ſhe inſiſts only upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1. That what Debts my Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> has payed due priot to the Marriage, with Sums of Money acquired and received during the Marriage, that ſhe ſhould have the Lyfe-rent of the ſame upon this ground; becauſe if theſe Debts had not been payed, they would have affected this Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> the Son; and he would have been lyable for the ſamen; ſo that in ſo far as the Son and Heir reaps Benefi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, by Imploying the ſums his Father received during the Marriage, for payment of Debts prior to the Marriage, for which otherwayes he would have been lyable, as repreſenting his Father, the <hi>Lady</hi> ought in ſo far to have right to the Lyfe-rent of the ſums with which the Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> payed the prior Debts 2. The Lord <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingtoun</hi> did not only reap Benefit by his Fathers payment of prior Debts with ſums of Money that he received during the Marriage, but alſo the ſubject that he has acquired by theſe ſums he received during the Marriage, being extant at the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the Marriage: The <hi>Lady</hi> by vertue of the foreſaid Clauſe in her Contract, muſt have Right to the Lyfe rent of what was acquired during the Marriage, and extant the time of the Husbands Deceaſe; and therefore in making the Compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of what the <hi>Lady</hi> ſhould have Right to Lyfe-rent, the Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi>'s condition, and the condition of the Eſtate is to be conſidered, as it was the time of the entry into the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and as it was at the time of the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſolution thereof; and in ſo far as the Eſtate is meliorat, and what the Lord <hi>Colling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toun</hi> had more at the Diſſolution of the Marriage, then he had the time of the entering into the Marriage, that muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood to have been acquired during the Marriage, and the <hi>Lady</hi> muſt have the Lyfe-rent of the ſamen; eſpecially ſeing in all ſuch caſes, where the Wife is provided to the Lyfe-rent of what ſhould be Conqueſt and Acquired during the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage: The <hi>Lords</hi> are alwayes in uſe to take Tryal of the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands Condition, the time of the entering into the Marriage, and of his Condition the time of the Diſſolution thereof; and what ever his Condition was better at that time, then it was at
<pb facs="tcp:42385:10"/>the time of the entring into the Marriage, that is eſteemed <hi>Conqueſce</hi> to give the Wife the Benefit of the Lyfe-rent of the ſamen, which is clear by ſeveral <hi>Deciſions,</hi> and particulary the 4th. of <hi>March</hi> 1623. <hi>Skeen</hi> contra <hi>Robieſon</hi>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Where the Husband by his Contract of Marriage being oblidged to give a Lyferent of the Conqueſce during the Marriage to his Wife, and the Fie to the Heirs of the Marriage: And he having acquired certain Lands and Fiſhings that did hold of the Town of</hi> Aberdeen <hi>in his Sons Name; and the Relict ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving purſued the Son, as repreſenting his Father upon the paſſive titles, for the lyfrent of the Lands and Fiſhings: And it being alledged that ſhe could not have the lyfrent of theſe Lands and Fiſhings becauſe by ane Act of the Town of</hi> Aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deen <hi>which was confirmed by the</hi> Queen, <hi>the Lands and Fiſhings could not be fewed nor lyfrented by a Woman; upon which the</hi> Lords <hi>found that albeit the Relict could not lyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent the Lands and Fiſhings, yet the Heir ſhould give her</hi> Damnum et intereſſe, <hi>becauſe the Husband could not be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to make any purchaſs that could prejudge the Wiſe of her lyfrent.</hi> And the 3d of <hi>July</hi> 1627. The <hi>Lady Dumferm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling contra the Earle her Son, Where by the contract of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, the</hi> Lady <hi>being provyded to all Lands that ſhould be conqueſt during the Marriage, and her Husband having ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired certain Lands during the Marriage, and taken the Rights in his Sons name, the</hi> Lords <hi>found that the</hi> Lady <hi>had the right of the lyfrent of the ſame: albeit it was alledged that the price of the Lands was not payed, but was reſting the time of his Fathers deceaſe, and that the Son as repreſenting him is ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for the ſame.</hi> And it is ſubjoin'd that the like <hi>Deciſion</hi> was done the 11 of <hi>Januar.</hi> 1632. <hi>The Lady</hi> Bonningtoun <hi>contra</hi> Hadden and the 27 of <hi>Jun.</hi> 1676 The <hi>Earl of</hi> Dumfermling <hi>contra the Earl of</hi> Callander, <hi>where the</hi> Lords <hi>found that a general Clauſe of Conqueſce did extend to what the Husband had acquyred during the Marriage, more then what he had the time of the contract of Marriage, &amp; with the burden of all his Debts contracted during the Marriage; that was eſteemed
<pb facs="tcp:42385:11"/>Conqueſce which was free over and above the debt contracted during the Marriage.</hi>
                  </q> By which it is evident that in ſo far as the Eſtate was meliorat, and in a better condition the time of the diſſolution of the Marriage, than it was the time of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, that was to be eſteemed <hi>Conqueſce;</hi> and that no debts were to be deduced, but theſe that were contracted during the Marriage. And as to the <hi>Deciſions</hi> adduced for the <hi>Lord Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingtoun</hi> the 26 of <hi>November.</hi> 1629 <hi>Where the</hi> Lords <hi>found that Lands being acquired be the Huſband from the Seller of the Lands, and thereafter diſponed in few again to the ſame ſeller for ane greater few duty than was contained in the ſellers pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors Rights, The augmentation of the few duty be the Husband could not be repute ane Conqueſce, whereof the Relict might Claim a lyfrent, as coming under the clauſe of Conqueſce of the contract,</hi> And in the caſe of <hi>James Wauchop contra the Laird of</hi> Niddrie, <hi>in the year</hi> 1683<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>where the husband having right to the Lands prior to the Marriage, and during the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage having acquired partial Rights, were not found to fall under the clauſe of Conqueſce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is anſwered that theſe <hi>Deciſions</hi> doe not meet this caſe; for as to that of the <hi>Lady Dumfermling againſt her Son,</hi> It was in the caſe betwixt a Superiour and a Vaſſal, where a Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or having purſued a Reduction againſt his Vaſſal, and the Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals rights being found null for want of Confirmation, and the Superiour having given a new right to the Vaſſall for augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the few-duty; that was not found <hi>Conqueſce,</hi> In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect there was no new acquiſition, the Superior having right to the Lands before the Marriage; and his right to the property of the <hi>few</hi> being only declared after the Marriage, by reduceing of the Vaſſals right; and therefore albeit the Superior gave a new right to the Vaſſal, augmenting the few-duty, That augmenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was not repute <hi>Conqueſce,</hi> to give the Relict the benefit of the lyfrent thereof: And that this was the caſe of that <hi>Deciſion,</hi> it is cleare by the <hi>Deciſion</hi> the laſt of <hi>June</hi> 1629. Betwixt the ſame Perſons. And as to the Caſe of <hi>Niddrie and his brother,</hi> firſt the queſtion there was, betwixt the <hi>Heir of Line,</hi> and the
<pb facs="tcp:42385:11"/>
                  <hi>Heir of Conqueſce</hi> of the ſecond Marriage, which does not meet in this caſe. Next the partial rights acquired by the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band after the Marriage, was found not to fall under the Clauſe of <hi>Conqueſce,</hi> in reſpect that the Husband had belonging to him of money, and other eſtate of great value, prior to the Marriage, of which, any ſums of money he depurſed after the Marriage in acquiring rights to the Lands, was the true product, and might be aſcribed to the ſums of money, and other eſtate which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to him before the Marriage.</p>
               <p>And as to the caſe of <hi>Cowan contra Young</hi> the 9th of <hi>Febru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary</hi> 1669, <hi>where a Father having given a bond of Proviſion of</hi> 400 <hi>pound to a Daughter of the firſt Marriage, was ſuſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and found to affect the Heir of Conqueſce of the Second Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage;</hi> And the 15 of <hi>July</hi> 1673 <hi>Robertſon contra Robertſon, where the</hi> Lords <hi>found that a clauſe in a contract of Marriage providing the lyfrent of the conqueſce to the Wife, did not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Husband to give competent proviſions to the Children;</hi> And <hi>Smith contra Muire,</hi> 23 December 1668. <hi>Where it was found, that ſuch a clauſe did not prejudge Creditors; but the Relict that intrometted with the moveables falling under the conqueſce, was found lyable for the Debt;</hi> And in the caſe of <hi>Frazer contra Cumming,</hi> the 8 of December 1687. <hi>Where the</hi> Lords <hi>found the Proviſion granted to the Children of the first Marriage was to be deduced out of the conqueſce in prejudice of the Relicts lyfrent, as alſo that his debts ought to be deduced and</hi> 11000 <hi>pound that he had reſerved to himſelfe be the contract of Marriage, and the ſuperplus only to be repute Conqueſce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is anſwered, that the caſe of <hi>Cowan</hi> &amp; <hi>Young,</hi> being betwixt a Child of the firſt Marriage and the Heir of Conqueſce in the ſecond Marriage, it did not meet the caſe of a lyfrenter; next it was only but a ſmall proviſion granted be a Father to his Child of the firſt Marriage, whom be the Law of Nature he is oblidg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to provide. As alſo in that Caſe the Heir of the ſecond Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage had a ſpecial proviſion, and ſomething alſo of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſce, ſo that the Fathers granting a moderate proviſion to a Child of the firſt Marriage, was not underſtood a defrauding
<pb facs="tcp:42385:12"/>of the Children of the ſecond Marriage. And the caſe of <hi>Robert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon contra Robertſon,</hi> albeit the <hi>Lords</hi> found, that ſuch clauſes could not exclude competent proviſions to the Children of the ſame Marriage, which was moſt Juſt, yet it is with this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs quality, that there were competent means, for a proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Mother remaining, and that the husband had done no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing fraudfully in prejudice of that clauſe. And the caſe of <hi>Smith and Muir,</hi> was betwixt a Relict and a Creditor, And it is not controverted but that a true and Lawful debt contracted by the Husband during the Marriage, ſhould deduce off the Conqueſce, And as to the Caſe of <hi>Frazer and Cumming</hi> it was thus, <hi>By contract of Marriage betwixt</hi> Alexander <hi>and</hi> Chriſtian Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers, <hi>The Husband did provide his Wife to ane certain yearly Annuitie in lyfrent, and likewayes to the lyfrent of the clauſe of conqueſce, reſerving to himſelf certain tenements of Lands and others extending to</hi> 11000 <hi>pounds; and all the queſtion there was in relation to the import of the Reſervation as to the</hi> 11000 <hi>Pounds, if the Husbands Debts ſhould affect the</hi> 11000 <hi>pounds, or be deduced out of the Conqueſce.</hi> Upon which the Lords <hi>found that the import of the clauſe of the Contract, is, that in the firſt place, There ought to be deduced out of the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands Eſtate extant the time of his Deceaſe, the Debts then due; and next that the</hi> 11000 <hi>Pounds is to be deduced, and what remains only is to be repute Conqueſce.</hi> By which it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that the 11000 Pounds that belonged to the Husband the time of the entring into the Marriage, was deduced in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the expreſs reſervation. And albeit a Husband may grant a Proviſion to a Child of the firſt Marriage, yet it will not follow, that he can do ſuch Deeds in defraud of the Relict, as may abſolutely evacuat the Clauſe. As alſo in that Caſe, the Relict had a ſpecial Lyfe-rent Proviſion, beſides the Lyfe-rent of the <hi>Conqueſce.</hi> And that <hi>Deciſion</hi> is ſo far from making againſt the <hi>Lady,</hi> that it makes expreſly for her: In ſua far as in that Caſe, the Lords ordained Probation to be led for proving the Condition of the Husbands Eſtate the time of entering into the Contract of Marriage; and
<pb facs="tcp:42385:12"/>what was the worth and value thereof the time of the Diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Marriage: To the effect that in ſua far as the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands Eſtate was better the time of the Diſſolution of the Marriage, than the time of the Contract: The Relict might have the benefit of the Lyferent thereof as <hi>Conqueſce.</hi> And as to any other <hi>Deciſion</hi> alledged upon for the Lord <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingtoun,</hi> they are either in the Caſe of a Competition betwixt the Heirs of a firſt and ſecond Marriage, or in the Caſe betwixt Heirs of ſecond Marriages and Creditors, which does not at all meet this Caſe.</p>
               <p>And whereas it is alledged, that the <hi>Lady</hi> has <hi>aliunde,</hi> a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Joyntute, albeit ſhe get nothing of the Lord <hi>Collingtoun,</hi> and ſo is not deſtitute of a Proviſion.</p>
               <p>It is anſwered, That albeit the <hi>Lady</hi> have a Joynture <hi>aliunde,</hi> yet ſeing ſhe has nothing from the Lord <hi>Collingtoun,</hi> except the Houſe and Yards of <hi>Collingtoun,</hi> which is not worth the ſpeaking of; yet that can be no Argument why ſhe ſhould not have a Joynture off the Lord <hi>Collingtoun,</hi> be vertue of that clauſe in her Contract of Marriage, his Father having received ſo great ſums of Money during the Marriage, partly out of the Ladie's Joynture, and partly out of his Penſions and Sallaries, by which he made his Eſtate ſo much in a better condition the time of the Diſſolution of the Marriage, than it was the time of the Contract: And albeit the Lady get a large Joynture<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet the Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> will not be deſtitute of a Proviſion, ſeing he has gotten a large Eſtate with his Lady.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>In reſpect whereof,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Additional Information for the Lady <hi>Caſtle-haven; againſt the Lord</hi> Collingtoun,</head>
               <p>TO evince the <hi>Ladie</hi>'s Claim beyond exception; and in anſwer to all the Practicks that have been, or can be obtruded: The Purſuer not only inſiſts upon the foreſaid clauſe anent the Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> his receiving payment of
<pb facs="tcp:42385:13"/>ſums of Money due to him during the Marriage: But farther doth preſs preceiſly the former clauſe of <hi>Conqueſce, viz.</hi> That the Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> hath Conqueſt and acquired ſums of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney during the Marriage: For ſeing that it is undeniable, that he hath cleared and reconqueſt his own Eſtate, which before, the Marriage was ſunk in more Debt then it was w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rth; and that this could not be done without his acquiring of ſums of Money: It is evident that he hath acquired ſums of Money, and that theſe acquiſitions are really ſtill extant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if not in <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie;</hi> yet in their undeniable effects. If the Purſuer were on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſiſting upon <hi>Collington</hi>'s Conqueſcing and Acquiring of Lands and Heretages, and urging that the Reconqueſcing of his Eſtate was a real Conqueſce. The practick touching the clearing of old Wodſets, and the purchaſing of acceſſional Rights<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and finding theſe to be no new Conqueſce of Lands, might be objected with ſome ſhew of reaſon; but the Caſe of theſe Practicks was only concerning Conqueſce of Lands, which is not the principal point now in Controverſie: But the point here urged is, That the Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> did purchaſe and acq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ire ſums of Money; and this is evidently made out both that he did acquire them, and that they are yet truly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant; ſo that its impoſſible to fruſtrate the Purſuer of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of this head of the Conqueſce, unleſs the Defender can as plainly make it out, that the Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> did Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſce the Eſtate, by ſums not of his own acquiring, but by the Defenders Tocher and Means, which can never be made out; ſeing the Conqueſce of the Eſtate doth far exceed all the Portion the Defender got with his Wife, and there is a great part of that yet unreceived. Neither is it to any purpoſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate here, how far the Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> might exhauſt his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſce by contracting of Debt, or doing other Rational Deeds, ſeing that the Debt which the Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> left at his Death, is always acknowledged, that it is to be deduced; and for other rational Deeds there is none can be alledged, except the conveyi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g of his Eſtate to his Son and appeirand Heir the Defender, which is no exhauſting, but a tranſmitting of the
<pb facs="tcp:42385:13"/>Conquer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to perform his Fathers obligment. Its true, it is alledged that the Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi>'s paying of his old Debts with the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys that he acquired, were rational Deeds: But it is as true, that theſe Deeds does no wayes exhauſt the Conqueſce, but rather eſtabliſh it: It being plainly ridiculous for a man to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that his getting and applying ſums of Money for the payment of his Debt, and clearing of his Eſtate, and thereby making himſelf Richer, ſhould be an exhauſting of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſce, ſince it is abſolutely the beſt evidence can be brought for it, and the beſt uſe that can be made of it; ſo that all the practicks about the exhauſting of rational Deeds are here Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent, and prove nothing. Nor is there the leaſt Injuſtice in what the Defender alledges for a great Abſurdity, <hi>viz. That the Heir Male of the Marriage (if any had been) ſhould by this means have carried away my</hi> Lord Collingtouns <hi>Estate from his Son in the former Marriage:</hi> For not to inſiſt upon the good Eſtate, the Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> hath got by his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, what could be more reaſonable then that the Heir Male of the Marriage ſhould have the Fee of what was really ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired during the Marriage.</p>
               <p>And there fore ſeing this Obligment of Conqueſce is made to the Purſuer in her Contract of Marriage, and that its undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able that the Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> did Conqueſce and Acquire ſums of Money, which are yet moſt really extant in their abiding effects: It is impoſſible the Lady can be deprived of her Lyfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent thereof, in ſua far as the ſums were truly acquired by him, and not brought into the Family by the Defender <hi>aliunde.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Information for my Lord <hi>Collingtoun,</hi> against. The Lady <hi>Caſtle-haven</hi> Relict of the deceast Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> his Father.</head>
               <p>WHen the deceaſed <hi>Lord Collingtoun</hi> was Married to his laſt <hi>Lady</hi> in <hi>Anno.</hi> 1661 he was under conſiderable burden of Debt; and leaſt my Ladies Joynture of 80 Chalders of Victual,
<pb facs="tcp:42385:14"/>by her former Husband might be affected by my Lords Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, ſeveral conveyances thereof were made in truſt and by the Contract of Marriage my Lord did Renounce his <hi>Jus mariti</hi> to the ſaid Joynture<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and took his hazard of what he might have otherwayes by my <hi>Lady,</hi> and farther my Lord bound and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidged him, <hi>that in caſe it ſhould happen him at any time dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Marriage betwixt him and his ſaid Lady, to conqueſce and aquire any ſums of Money. Lands or Heretages, or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive payment of ſums of Money due to him; in that caſe, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy the ſamen in favours of himſelf and his future Spouſe in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct fie and lyfrent, and the Heirs male to be procreat betwixt them, which failing to my Lord, his other Heirs who are appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſucceed him in his other Lands and Heretages</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is a proceſs at the <hi>Ladies</hi> inſtance againſt this Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> as repreſenting his Father upon the paſſive Titles, libelling that "<hi>the defunct did after the Marriage, conqueſce and acquire the Sum of</hi> 260000 <hi>Merks,</hi> and concluds that the <hi>defender ſhould be decerned to imploy the ſame for the Purſuers Lyferent uſe:</hi> And urges that concluſion upon the clauſe of the Contract of Marriage above mentioned, containing two ſeparate and diſtinct obligments: The one, <hi>To take the Lands, Heretages, and ſums of Money to be Conqueſced during the Marriage:</hi> And the other, <hi>To Imploy all ſums of Money due to him, whereof he ſhould receive payment, during the Marriage, likewiſe to my</hi> Ladie<hi>'s Lyferent uſe;</hi> Whereby it doth appear, that my Lady did not intend to reſt upon a clauſe of <hi>Conqueſt</hi> in the uſual Style, but did farther provide for her own ſecurity, by adjecting the poſterior Clauſe, oblidging my <hi>Lord</hi> to imploy all ſums of Money to be received during the Marriage, to her liferent uſe, which was moſt Juſt and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, ſeing my <hi>Lords</hi> condition at the time did not ſuffer him to ſecure any preſent joynture, his Eſtate being affected with many incumbrances, it was therefore highly reaſ nable that what ever ſums he ſhould receive during the Marriage, ſhould be ſecured for her liferent uſe.</p>
               <p>It was anſwered for the Defender denying the paſſive Titles,
<pb facs="tcp:42385:14"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> theſe Clauſes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the contract of Marriage, unleſs the Purſuer will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend upon Lands, Heretages, ſums of Money, Conqueſt <hi>during</hi> the Marriage, and extant unconſumed at the <hi>Diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> thereof: Or that the <hi>Defunct</hi> had received ſums of Money due to him <hi>the time of the contract</hi> of Marriage: for as to the Clauſe of <hi>Conqueſce,</hi> There has been no point in our Law more fully and clearly determined, than the Import thereof both in relation to Heirs of Proviſion and Relicts in Contracts of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage: for the various circumſtances of Children, or Relicts having the benefit of thoſe Clauſes, have prompted them upon ſeveral Specialities, to endeavour the extenſions of ſuch Clauſes in their Favours, upon ſome pretences of differences from the Caſes formerly decided, whereby upon conſideration of the moſt important <hi>Deciſions</hi> in that point, it will appear that the Lords have ſcarce ever varied, ſince there were Practicks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Record, anent the import of Clauſes of <hi>Conqueſce,</hi> which they have ever found to give Relicts, or Heirs of Proviſions, the Benefit of what Conqueſt did remain unconſumed at the death of the Husband, or Father; and that ſuch Clauſes could not hinder the <hi>Acquirer</hi> from the full, free, and unaccountable Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of his own Eſtate during his Life, and to diſpoſe of his own by any juſt or rational Deed at his pleaſure: pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding that nothing were done fraudulently for evacuating of ſuch Clauſes. <hi>And farther,</hi> The Deeds of the <hi>Acquirer</hi> are not only ſuſtained when the Conqueſce is conſumed, but even when the Conqueſce of Lands, Heretages, or ſums of Money is extant at the diſſolution of the Matriage; the ſame is affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and burdened with all the Debts of the <hi>Acquirer,</hi> not only for onerous, but alſo for gratuitous Cauſes; there being always a juſt and rational conſideration, ſuch as the Proviſion of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with ſuitable Portions; and even a Proviſion of an eldeſt Son hath been frequently ſuſtained as a paternal Deed; and if in any Caſe gratuitous Debts or Deeds, of the <hi>Acquirer</hi> have been annulled, at the inſtance of Relicts, or Children of a Marriage; the ſame has always been upon the head of Fraud,
<pb facs="tcp:42385:15"/>or that there was no juſt cauſe for making ſuch Deeds, and theſe Deeds are not only ſuſtained in favours of <hi>Creditors</hi> to affect the Conqueſce, but they have even been ſuſtained as bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens upon the Conqueſce, whereby Relicts or Heirs of Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on have no Action againſt the Repreſentatives of the <hi>Acquirer,</hi> to Disburſt the Conqueſt of theſe Debts: The <hi>Deciſions</hi> in this matter are ſo numerous, and the Caſes ſo various, that it were tedious to relate them; but the <hi>Defender</hi> did both in his Debate, and by a particular Note a part offer a few of them to the Lords conſideration, whereby it will appear, that the ground of all is one, <hi>viz. That Conqueſce is burdened with all rational Deeds of Adminiſtration of the Acquirer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the ſecond Clauſe, whereby it is pretended, that, <hi>All ſums of Money due during the Marriage, and received by the Defunct, ought to be Imployed for the Purſuers Liferent uſe.</hi> It is anſwered, That the Lords are intreated to conſider the Clauſe as it ſtands in the Contract, which is very far from Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting that Senſe which is fixed upon it: For by the firſt Clauſe, the Conqueſce during the Marriage was deſigned to be ſecured in the ordinary Style of Conqueſce: And by the ſecond all ſums due to my Lord before the Marriage, were deſigned to be ſecured to my Lady, and that which was in Proſpect, was a Debt due upon the Eſtate of <hi>Huntley;</hi> And my Lord had juſt ground to expect, that the ſame might have been made effectual to him, who was then in great Favour, and had ſuffered much for the King; and it was not ſit to expreſs the Debt particularly in the Contract, leaſt being propaled, it might have been affected by his Creditors; and as this was the true Communing, ſo it is impoſſible the words of the Clauſe can bear another Senſe, which runs in theſe Terms, <hi>viz. He obliged himſelf in caſe it ſhould happen, him to purchaſe, or acquire ſums of Money, Lands, or Heretages, or to receive payment of Debts due to him, to imploy,</hi> &amp;c. Whereof the conſtruction of the laſt Clauſe is, in caſe he ſhall happen to receive payment of ſums due to him, where <hi>Sums due,</hi> muſt in propriety of Language ſignify a <hi>Preterit,</hi> that the ſums
<pb facs="tcp:42385:15"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turo,</hi> was in caſe it ſhould happen him to receive theſe ſums: And the proſpect of receiving of ſums, muſt alwayes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſe the ſums due. And the firſt end of the Clauſe relating to <hi>Purchaſe</hi> of ſums thereafter, the natural <hi>Alternative</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to that Proviſion, is ſums dew already, whereby all ſums were ſecured to my Lady, whether due before, or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed after the Contract, with the legal burden of my Lords full and free Adminiſtration during the Marriage. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the words of the Clauſe (as the Purſuer would conſtruct them) run thus, <hi>In caſe it ſhould happen my</hi> Lord <hi>during the Marriage to receive payment of ſums deue;</hi> even this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, though it be not natural, or ſuitable to the Clauſe, yet it alters not the Caſe one hairs breadth: For in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction the words <hi>(during the Marriage)</hi> which ſignify <hi>Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turition,</hi> have not the leaſt relation to ſums due, which are ſtill in <hi>Preterito;</hi> but they do only relate to the receipt of the Money: So the Clauſe doth import, that if ſums then due ſhould be received during the Marriage, they were to be Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed; but it is altogether force againſt the natural con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to mention theſe words, <hi>During the Marriage,</hi> In the firſt Clauſe, which can neither relate to the Receipt of the Money: Becauſe if that Money upon the Eſtate of <hi>Huntely</hi> ſhould be received or ſecured, though after the Diſſolution of the Marriage, the Purſuer would have a Liferent thereof by the Clauſe, which ſhe could not claim, if the condition run, <hi>In caſe during the Marriage the Money were rece ved:</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it poſſible that the words, <hi>During the Marriage,</hi> can relate to ſums due: For <hi>Sums due during the Marriage,</hi> is Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe, <hi>Sums due,</hi> being <hi>Preterite,</hi> and <hi>during the Marriage,</hi> being then <hi>Future;</hi> unleſs for my Ladies Conveniency, ſhe be allowed to add a word or two, to make the Senſe as ſhe would have it; and that ſhe ſhould be permitted to Interpret the Clauſe, in thir Terms, <hi>viz Sums falling due, or becoming due during the Marriage,</hi> For without the Addition of theſe words, or other of the like Import, it is impoſſible in na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure
<pb facs="tcp:42385:16"/>that ever the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e words <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> by any conſtruction that can be forced upon the Clauſe, as it ſtands: And if ſuch violence were put upon it, then it would ſtill diſagree with what has been evidently communed, <hi>viz, That</hi> Huntleys <hi>Debt already due ſhould be Liferented, if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived:</hi> For if only ſums falling or becoming due <hi>Thereafter,</hi> were to be imployed, then there were no Obligation, as to theſe which were <hi>already</hi> due; And it would be a wonderful ſtreatch that could make the ſame words ſignify both <hi>Preterite</hi> and <hi>Future.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secundo,</hi> Suppoſe the words of the Clauſe ſhould be ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (as the Purſuer contends) to an Obligment of <hi>Imploying all ſums due during the Marriage;</hi> yet it is not poſſible to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Importance of that Clauſe, farther than an ordinary clauſe of Conqueſce; and conſequently the <hi>Husbands</hi> Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would only be preſtable with the burden of all rational Deeds: For the Clauſe of Conqueſce oblidges, to beſtow, <hi>All ſums of Money Conqueſt during the Marriage:</hi> And the ſecond Clauſe obliges (as is pretended) to Imploy, <hi>All ſums falling due during the Marriage to be received by the Defunct;</hi> Which is all one Clauſe; for all ſums falling due during the Marriage, that the Defunct could receive, muſt be ſums <hi>Conqueſt</hi> during the Marriage; and conſequently if the Obligment to imploy the Conqueſce, cannot ſecure the Purſuer from the burden of all rational Deeds, neither can the Oblidgment of imploying ſums falling due, which is the ſame thing: And it is not the variation of the Style, or words, that will evert the effect of ſuch a train of <hi>Deciſions;</hi> nor is it poſſible that the <hi>Defunct,</hi> or any reaſonable man would have agreed to ſuch an extravagant Clauſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all his Fortune was then wholly over-burdened, ſo he ſhould have been Incapacitate for ever to render it in a better condition for himſelf, or his Heirs: For though in this Caſe there be eventually no Children of the Marriage, which might probably have exiſted, my Lady being then little paſt 40. And being as careful to provide for them, as her ſelf; yet if they had exiſted, the Defunct would have been Incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citate
<pb facs="tcp:42385:16"/>that his eldeſt Son might ſucceed, which in conſequence would have drawn his Creditors upon him; that he could not have had his perſon ſafe, when they found that he could not apply one ſixpence for their payment out of what he had, or could acquire.</p>
               <p>It was replyed, that the Purſuers Lybel is moſt Relevant, both upon the <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> and ſubſequent Clauſe: And albeit, the Purſuer doth not alledge, that any ſums of Money, Lands, or Heretages, Conqueſt during the Marriage, are extant, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Defunct did apply theſe ſums acquired, and falling due during the Marriage, for payment of the Debts affecting the Eſtate and Lands of <hi>Collingtoun.</hi> The Defunct being <hi>Locu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletior factus,</hi> by applying theſe ſums for the Relief of his own Eſtate, which by the Conrract ought to have been imployed for the Puſuers Lyferent uſe, the Lady ought to have the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit thereof, and doth not claim any Lyferent of ſums ſpent and conſumed; but where there is ane exiſting benefit inriching the Defunct, ſhe ought to have a lyfrent of the Lands releived to which ſhe reſtricts her lybel, and craves no more neither upon the firſt nor ſecond Clauſe of the Contract. 2. <hi>Conqueſce</hi> in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of Wives or Children, is alwayes underſtood in ſo far as the <hi>Husband</hi> is richer at the <hi>Diſſolution</hi> of the Marriage, than he was at the time of the <hi>Contract,</hi> And the defunct being richer in the value of the hail Lands redeemed, my Lady ought to have the lyfrent thereof. 3 Deciſions in matters of <hi>Conqueſce</hi> have varied according to the circumſtances of the caſes Debated, and all of them have this notable difference from the Purſuers Caſe, that in theſe <hi>Deciſions,</hi> the Relict had ſpecial ſuitable proviſions, and the <hi>Conqueſts</hi> were only adjected as general uncertaine Clauſes upon which the Relicts did not depend, But here there is no ſpecial proviſion, except the Houſe and Yeards of <hi>Collingtoun,</hi> and all that was depended upon, was the clauſe of <hi>Conqueſce</hi> which was adviſed by my Lord <hi>Dirling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toun,</hi> and eminent Lawyers, who thought fitter to take the defunct obliged in the termes of the Contract than to take a
<pb facs="tcp:42385:17"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap> it cannot be imagined that ſo eminent a Lawyer would adviſe a clauſe that would be abſolutely <hi>Eluſory,</hi> tho' the defunct made his fortune during the Marriage, 4. There are alſo ſeveral <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions</hi> which fortify the purſuers Caſe, as particularely a deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion <hi>Skeen</hi> contra <hi>Robertſon.</hi> 4 <hi>March</hi> 1624. where <hi>a band of Proviſion to a Daughter was found to be lyable to the Relicts lyfrent by her clauſe of Conqueſce.</hi> And in the ſame caſe, the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band having acquired right to a <hi>Salmond</hi> Fiſhing near <hi>Aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deen,</hi> which by the cuſtom of the place could not be bruiked by a Woman, yet the relict by her <hi>Conqueſce</hi> was found to have <hi>utilem actionem againſt the heir for the value,</hi> And in the caſe of the Counteſs of <hi>Dumfermting</hi> againſt her Son (Lands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conqueſt originally in the name of the eldeſt Son) the Counteſs was <hi>found to have right, to Lyfrent theſe Lands tho' never in the Perſon of the Father,</hi> The like <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> Where a Right originally acquired in the name of a ſecond Son, was alſo affected by the Relicts lyfrent, upon a clauſe of Conqueſt. 50 The <hi>Deciſions</hi> adduced in the Caſe of Children provided to Conqueſce, import nothing; becauſe all Children doe repreſent the Defunct, in ſo far as they have benefite by him; whereas the Relicts are moſt favourable Creditors, and the <hi>Deciſions</hi> adduced in the caſe of Relicts are of no moment, as that Lands conqueſced, or burdened with the Debts due ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly for the purchaſe thereof, nothing being reckoned but with deduction of Debts during the Marriage. And in the caſe of the Lady <hi>Dumfermling</hi> againſt her Son 26. <hi>November.</hi> 1629. Where the Superiour having acquired the property of <hi>Fews,</hi> and having again fewed the ſame Land for greater <hi>Few duties,</hi> Theſe additional <hi>Few duties</hi> were not reckoned Conqueſce, Becauſe the Right of the <hi>Fews</hi> came to the Huſband by Vertue of Irritancies contained in the Fewars Charters, incurred before the Marriage, and whereby no duty out of theſe Lands could be reckoned Conqueſce during the Marriage. 6. The Purſuer did not reſt in a ſingle clauſe of <hi>Conqueſce</hi> to which all the <hi>Deciſions</hi> did relate, but did farther provide for
<pb facs="tcp:42385:17"/>her Security by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to imploy all <hi>Sums during the Marriage,</hi> which muſt at leaſt oblige the Defunct in ſo far as he and his Heires were <hi>Lucrati</hi> by imploying theſe ſums for the reliefe of his Eſtate, which clauſe muſt either have that import, or none at all; For no body can imagine that the Purſuer would conſider that uncertain claim upon <hi>Huntlies</hi> Eſtate to be of any value, and if nothing elſe had been conſidered, that would have been particularly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt: and it was moſt rational that the Defunct ſhould grant ſuch an obligement, Becauſe my Lady by the conveyance of her Joynture did ſecure 36. <hi>Chalders</hi> Victual for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Family, which being ſufficient for maintenance, and all neceſſary expences, it was moſt Juſt that what other ſums might be received by the Defunct, ſhould be imployed for the Ladies lyfrent uſe, yet notwithſtanding of the ſetlement at the Contract, It is offered to be proven that my Lord by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf did intromet with 24. Chalders of the victual allocat for the entertainment of the Family, by which means my Lady was neceſſitat to take up her Joynture in the <hi>North,</hi> which ſhe had diſponed to her Children at the time of the Contract, and to conſume the ſame for the Intertainment of the Defuncts Family. So that it cannot be thought an invidious claim, that my Lady ſhould deſire her lyfrent, equivalent to the debts payed by that part of the Joynture, which was allocat to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement of the Family.</p>
               <p>It was duplied, that all the pretences inſiſted upon Joyntly or ſeparatly have no ſhaddow of relevancy in them, and 1ſt, As to the firſt Alledgance <hi>viz.</hi> That the Purſuer inſiſts only for a lyfrent of what is extant Conqueſce during the Marriage, by relieving the Eſtate that was overburdened, and thereby was <hi>Locupletior factus.</hi> It is anſwered, that as the lybel could not relevantly conclude the imployment of all ſums purchaſed and received during the Marriage, but with the burden of all ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Deeds So neither can it be ſuſtained, as it is now reſtricted, for the lyfrent of the Lands relieved, and <hi>in quantum</hi> the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funct was <hi>Lucratus;</hi> becauſe Law doth allow all Husbands a
<pb facs="tcp:42385:18"/>free and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ull Adminiſtration, and they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of Conqueſce for what is conſumed by that adminiſtration, and as they might have waſted, and ſpent all unprofitably, ſo much more might they apply the ſame for payment of debts, which is not only a rational but a neceſſary deed, and if the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors had not found the Defunct ſo juſt in his Inclinations, they would have compelled him thereto, either by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal diligence, or by affecting his Eſtate; and the pretence of <hi>Locupletior factus</hi> imports nothing, unleſs the Purſuer could ſubſume in the terms of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligment that the Defunct had been <hi>Locupletior factus</hi> in Lands, Heretages, or ſums of Money, which here cannot be alledged; for the Defunct was only <hi>Locupletior factus,</hi> by payment of his urgent Debts, which is neither a frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent adminiſtration, nor was he thereby enriched in the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars</hi> enumerat in the clauſe of Conqueſce; and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly my Lady had no Intereſt in that gain: for clauſes of Conqueſce are ſtrictly interpret, and never extended beyond the preciſe Words; therfore a wife having right to Conqueſce of Lands, hath no right to ſums acquired, and ſhe who has right to Lands and ſums, has no right to Victual, Pleniſhing, Plate, Jewels, or moveables of any ſort, So that if the Defunct at his deceaſe had been worth 10000 pounds Sterling, in other moveables than ſums of Money, the Purſuer could not have acclaimed any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt therein, which may ſatisfy the <hi>Lords</hi> that there was not ſuch an anxious concerne to make this Conqueſce ſecure, when Goods and Geir and all moveables were omitted in the Clauſe, which are oft provided as Conqueſce, and as the Defunct had power to have turned all his free Eſtate in ſuch moveables, ſo much more could he pay his urgent Debts, and releive his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Eſtate, without providing the ſame to his Lady, and the Children of his ſecond Marriage, to the excluſion of his legal Heirs, 2. The releiving of the Lands of <hi>Collingtoun<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> cannot in Law be reckoned a Conqueſce of theſe Lands, becauſe a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſce Is a new <hi>few</hi> to which the Defunct neither did, nor could ſucceed, as Heire to any of his Predeceſſors: and the Defender
<pb facs="tcp:42385:18"/>deſires that the Purſuer would condeſcend upon any former practick, where ever a Wife or Heirs of proviſion did pretend that a <hi>Husband,</hi> or <hi>Father,</hi> could not pay his Debts in prejudice of a Conqueſce; ſo that if there be little decided in this, it is becauſe few or none have ever pretended to call it in Queſtion; on the contrary all that is found to approach to this Caſe, is a debate betwixt the Counteſs of <hi>Dumfermling</hi> and her Son 26. <hi>November.</hi> 1629. And <hi>Fraſer</hi> contra <hi>Fraſer</hi> lately decided. By the firſt of which <hi>Deciſions,</hi> the Lords found <q>
                     <hi>That the Earl of</hi> Dumfermling <hi>having acquired the right of property of certain fews during the Marriage which he fewed out again for greater few-duties, that the Counteſs had no intereſt in theſe additional Few duties by the clauſe of Conqueſce.</hi>
                  </q> And whereas it is pretended that the ground of this <hi>Deciſion</hi> was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Fews</hi> were declared Null, upon irritancies before the Marriage, this alledgance, is <hi>gratis dictum</hi> and without the leaſt veſtige of reaſon from the <hi>Deciſion,</hi> which was upon juſt grounds; becauſe the <hi>Earl</hi> having a <hi>Dominium Directum,</hi> any improvement of that <hi>Dominium</hi> during the Marriage was not regarded as a Conqueſce. And the Lords had formerly great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to this <hi>Deciſion,</hi> in the caſe of the Laird of <hi>Niddrie</hi> againſt his Brother; where the Father having a right upon the Lands of <hi>Lochtoure</hi> preceeding the ſecond Marriage, albeit the ſame would have been ineffectual in competition with Rights acquir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed during the ſecond Marriage, yet the Lords found, <hi>that the poſterior rights were preſumed to have been acquired for vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dating and compleating the anterior Right, and that they did accreſce thereto, and the Son of the ſecond Marriage had no in-Intereſt therein as Conqueſce</hi> And in the caſe of <hi>Fraſer</hi> and <hi>Fraſer,</hi> the Husband at his Contract did put a valuation upon the Eſtate he had over and above certaine Ackers of Land, which he declared ſhould not be eſtimate any part of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſce, yet the Relict having acclaimed a lyfrent of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſce during the Marriage, the following points were therein decided <hi>viz.</hi> 1 That the Father having immediatly after the ſecond Contract provided 6000 <hi>Merks,</hi> to his eldeſt Son,
<pb facs="tcp:42385:19"/>beſide the forſaid capital of 11000 <hi>pounds,</hi> and his Daughter to 5000. <hi>Merks,</hi> and allowed 1000 <hi>pounds</hi> for her Wedding Cloaths, and having payed a great part of theſe ſums very ſhortly after the Contract, before it was poſſible to have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired ſo much money as could have payed the ſame, yet the Lords found, <hi>that theſe ſums ſo contracted, and payed, were not to be taken off the capital of</hi> 11000 pound <hi>of his Estate before the Marriage, but the whole capital foreſaid behoved to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced before reckoning the Conqueſce at the Diſſolution</hi> 2. In that caſe, they found that <hi>all Debts were to be deduced, both thoſe that were prior, and thoſe that were poſterior to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage;</hi> as appears by the debate immediatly preceeding the Interloquitor, which was done upon deliberation by the whole Lords, and thereafter repreſented of new by two ſeveral Bills, containing the whole favourable circumſtances of the Caſe, and particularly that the Relict had but a very mean proviſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Conqueſce, upon which ſhe could not live; all which appears by the forſaid Decreet, marked at the ſeveral debates and interloquitors; and what is now pretended is far leſs fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable then any of theſe Caſes.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond alledging, that <hi>Conqueſce</hi> is alwayes under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, in ſua far as the Husband was richer at the <hi>Diſſolution</hi> then at the <hi>Contract</hi> of Marriage. It is anſwered that the grounds abovementioned doe fully ſatisfy this pretence, for the eſtimation of the Husbands being <hi>Richer,</hi> muſt be made with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to theſe particulars whereof the Contract is provided to the Wife; and if the Husband have provided a Wife to lyfrent the Conqueſt, Lands, and Heretages only; it is not to be conſidered how far the <hi>Husband</hi> is become <hi>Richer</hi> in ſums of Money, Goods and Geir, whereof, the <hi>Wife</hi> hath no clauſe of Conqueſce, or if the proviſion of Conqueſce be of Lands, Heretages, and ſums of Money, as in this caſe, tho' the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band had purchaſed a great Eſtate in Jewels, Plate, Victual, Cattel, or any moveables, that is not to be conſidered but only how far he is become richer in Lands, Heretages, and ſums Conqueſt which is not pretended in this Caſe but only that
<pb facs="tcp:42385:19"/>he is richer by payment of his Debts, and re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eiving of his Lands. And ſeing my Lady did not take my Lord oblidged to imploy all Goods, Geir, and movables whatſomever, it is a demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration that ſhe did not intend to tie him ſo cloſs as is now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, but left to his own diſcretion whether he would enrich himſelf in theſe particulars provided for her lifrent-uſe, or in others wherein ſhe had no intereſt.</p>
               <p>To the third, it is admired that the Lady ſhould recur to <hi>Deciſions</hi> to fortify her pretence, for in all the <hi>Deciſions</hi> for above ſixty years there is no variation, except in that pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Deciſion</hi> adduced be the Purſuer <hi>Skeen</hi> contra <hi>Robertſon,</hi> which has not been ſeen by the Defender not being in <hi>Durie</hi> nor any citted known Writter, and whereof the circumſtances doe not appear, and all others doe agree in this, <hi>that a Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, or Father, may not only do all onerous Deeds, but may give Liberalities and Gratuities even to Children, or to the Heir where there is a rational Cauſe, much more may urgent Debts be payed, whereto the Acquirer could be compelled.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as to the only defence againſt all the <hi>Deciſions,</hi> upon the ſingularity, <hi>that the Purſuer had no ſpecial proviſion, and that by the advice of an eminent</hi> Lawyer. <hi>It was thought fitter to take theſe general Clauſes, then a proviſion of</hi> 3000 Merks <hi>yearly,</hi> It is anſwered, this ſpeciality makes no alteration, it being impoſſible to find different Caſes, ſo perfectly agreing, but ſome circumſtances will vary, but here the rule of the Lords <hi>Deciſions</hi> is, that all rational Deeds ſhall be ſuſtained, and if this be ſuch a circumſtance, that it renders the payment of the Debt in prejudice of the Conqueſce, fraudulent, then it is relevant but not otherways, and ſtill there is to be a difference wade betwixt firſt and ſecond Contracts of Marriage, for if a man in his firſt Contract of Marriage gave no ſpecial proviſion, but a clauſe of Conqueſce, whereby if the Husband ſhould vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarly evacuat the Conqueſce, the Wife of his youth, and Mother of his Children would become deſtitute and miſerable, It were infamous in him to evacuate ſuch a <hi>Conqueſce,</hi> except by inevitable Deeds; and any voluntary Deed would in Juſtice
<pb facs="tcp:42385:20"/>be reckoned fraudulent; but in a ſecond contract where there is no portion, but a joynture that returns at diſſolution, the like favour is not due. For if the Relict have an honourable provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, whether by the firſt or ſecond Marriage, it imports not, yea there is nothing more ordinary then that Heireſſes do content themſelves with the lifrent of their own Heretages, and oft times with leſs, yet in the caſe <hi>Robertſon</hi> againſt <hi>Robertſon</hi> 15th <hi>July</hi> 1673. It is plead for the Rclict who was Wife of the firſt Marriage, that ſhe had only an clauſe of Conqueſce, and no ſpecial proviſion, yet a bond originally taken in the name of the eldeſt Son during the Marriage, was ſuſtained againſt her, unleſs there were not ſufficient means for a competency to her <hi>Aliunde,</hi> in which caſe the Lords found, <hi>the bond would be fraudulent;</hi> and there is no queſtion the Lady was very well adviſed in relation to theſe Caſes ſhe deſired advice in, as how to convoy her Joynture, which was done to ſo good effect, that the Defunct with all the Influence and right of a Husband, could never come to one ſixpence of the <hi>North-Countrey</hi> Joynture; but theſe Clauſes were never adviſed by a Lawyer to have any ſpecial effect, whereof the Lords may be ſatisfied by the Purſuers own Aſſertion, that 3000 Merks of Joynture was offered; and was there ever any Lawyer that would prefer a general Clauſe of Conqueſce to a ſpecial Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, which has a preference as to Moveables, to all Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and is uſually the beſt ſecured real Debt; ſo that the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glecting of a ſpecial Proviſion, is a demonſtration that there was no Liferent under proſpect, and that the Clauſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſce was adjected of meer Stile and Formality. And Sir <hi>Andrew Gilmour</hi> who drew the Contract, would never have agreed to ſo unreaſonable Clauſes as theſe in the Contract are, according to the Purſners Interpretation, he being the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>functs Brother in Law.</p>
               <p>To the Fourth, There was nothing ever decided contrary to what is now pleaded: for the Deciſion finding, <hi>That the Wife had Right to the value of a Fiſhing in</hi> Aberdeen, <hi>which by the cuſtom of the place could not be bruiked by a Woman,</hi> was
<pb facs="tcp:42385:20"/>moſt ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> like the Earl of <hi>Dumfermling</hi> Acquiring Lands in the Name of his eldeſt Son, was juſtly found, <hi>To have done a fraudulent Deed to evacuate the Conqueſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> Yet betwixt the ſame Parties, it was alſo found, <hi>That the Earl having firſt acquired a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Tack of the ſame Lands during the Marriage, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards baving acquired the property, the Ladies Lyferent of the Lands extended no farther, than to the Tack-Duty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Tack firſt acquired;</hi> On this ground, that the Lady was not provided to the Lyferent of Tacks, albeit it might have ſeemed that the Tack was extinguiſhed by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty: But ſtill the Lords do reſtrict theſe Clauſes as much as they can bear.</p>
               <p>As to the Fifth, Pretending to Anſwer the <hi>Deciſions</hi> addu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, it is anſwered, That the <hi>Deciſions</hi> in caſe of Heirs of Conqueſce, do by much more ſtrong reaſon cut off the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of this Purſuers proceſs. For Heirs of Conqueſce, are more favourable in relation to Conqueſce than Relicts; as was expreſly found in the Caſe of the Lady <hi>Kilbocho,</hi> againſt the <hi>Laird;</hi> and Lady <hi>Rentoune</hi> againſt the <hi>Laird,</hi> where Lands Conqueſt were burdened with annual-rents of a part of the price reſting, albeit in both the Lords declared they would have found otherwiſe in the Caſe of Heirs of Conqueſce, ſo that Heirs of Conqueſce being more favourable than Relicts, what ever doth exclude their Intereſt in Conqueſce, muſt much more exclude the Relicts Intereſt, and the pretence that Heirs of Conqueſce do repreſent the Defunct, whereas Relicts are Creditors, is of no moment, becauſe in competition with Creditors, they are conſidered as Heirs, but in reſpect of the Heirs of Lyne (which is the Caſe of all the <hi>Deciſions</hi>) they are moſt favourable Creditors.</p>
               <p>To the Sixth, Founding upon the laſt Clauſe of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract anent <hi>ſums due during the Marriage,</hi> alledged to be inſert for a farther Security than the common Clauſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſce, which varies this Caſe from all theſe beſide it. It is anſwered, The Defender hopes he has already ſufficiently
<pb facs="tcp:42385:21"/>cleared, that by the conſtruction of the words in the Contract, nothing is comprehended that <hi>fell due after the Marriage. Et ſeparatim,</hi> it is hoped that the Reaſons already adduced, why the import of that Clauſe (as the Purſuer would have it) ſignifies no more than a common Clauſe of <hi>Conqueſce,</hi> and conſequently muſt be ſubject to the ſaids burdens, and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded with the ſame <hi>Deciſions,</hi> and the force of what hath been ſaid, is the more evident, that the Purſuer found her ſelf obliged to recede from the firſt concluſion of the <hi>Summonds,</hi> for <hi>Imploying all ſums due, and received, without exception,</hi> and did reſtrict the ſame to the ſums imployed for the <hi>Payment of Debt,</hi> and <hi>in quantum Lucratus;</hi> whereby it is evident that Law does not ſuſtain ſuch an Obligment to imploy <hi>All ſums received</hi> in the full Latitude of the Clauſe. And if it cannot be effectual as it ſtands in the Style of words, we muſt then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what is the Cauſe, why Law reſtricts the effect of ſuch Obligments, and we ſhall find the Cauſe to be the ſame why Law reſtricts the effect of <hi>Conqueſce,</hi> as being againſt the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and meaning of Parties, the rights of Property and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, and that ſuch Clauſes are only <hi>Deſtinations.</hi> Again, if we conſider the Syle of both Clauſes; Clauſes of <hi>Conqueſce</hi> are as peremptor to imploy <hi>all ſums Conqueſced,</hi> as this is alledged to be for <hi>ſums during the Marriage.</hi> And ſeing the laſt Clauſe cannot be effectual in the full Latitude more than the firſt, what other eſtimate can be made thereof, than the known Marches and Land Marks, by which the <hi>Lords</hi> have bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the effect of <hi>Conqueſce.</hi> And as clauſes of Conqueſce do eaſily run in relation to ſums purchaſed and acquired; ſo ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a clauſe of Conqueſce ſhould run in theſe Terms, <hi>All ſums Purchaſed, Acquired and received during the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage;</hi> can it be ſuppoſed that the word <hi>(Received)</hi> ſhould make an alteration in the Caſe; or are not ſums <hi>Acquired</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Marriage, <hi>Purchaſed?</hi> And are not ſums <hi>Purchaſed, Received</hi> during the Marriage? So the terms being Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, they cannot vary the Deciſion. 2. <hi>Et ſeparatim,</hi> tho' it had been the expreſs meaning of Parties, to have obliged
<pb facs="tcp:42385:21"/>the De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> to be Received by him;</hi> yet ſuch an Obligation could not have been effectual in Law: Becauſe a Husband by his <hi>Jus Mariti</hi> hath right to all moveable ſums falling under <hi>Communion of Goods:</hi> And farther his right thereto is unaccountable, and the <hi>Jus mariti</hi> of an Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, it is ſo fixed and inſured by Law, that <hi>inhaerit Oſſibus,</hi> and cannot poſſibly be renounced in favours of the Wife, by any deed of the Husbands directly nor indirectly: Whereas by this clauſe as it is interpreted, the Husband ſhould be effectually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuded of his <hi>Jus mariti</hi> in favours of his Wife, in ſo far as he would thereby be accountable to his Wife for her lyfrent-uſe, for his intromiſſion with <hi>moveable ſums,</hi> which in Law do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to him unaccountably. And as it is not controverted that the <hi>Jus Mariti</hi> doth imply an unaccountable right in the Perſon of the Husband, ſo it hath been found on moſt Juſt grounds that this right is incommunicable to the Wife, in the caſe of the Lady <hi>Pilton</hi> againſt <hi>Hay</hi> of <hi>Balhouſie</hi> 2d. <hi>February.</hi> 1667. Where a bond of 1000. <hi>Merks</hi> yearly being granted to a Wife to be diſpoſed of as ſhe pleaſed, ſecluding the Husbands <hi>Jus Mariti;</hi> The Lords found that <hi>payment made to the Husband, without the Wifs conſent, did exoner the Debitor, and exclude the Wifs executors:</hi> Which clears that a right could not be ſo qualified, but that it behoved to be Simply tranſmitted to the Husband, or null. But for farther evidence, that even the <hi>deed of the Husband himſelf cannot divest him of his Right,</hi> It was ſound 13, <hi>July</hi> 1678 that a <hi>Husband having renounced his</hi> Jus mariti <hi>to a part of his Wifes Joynture in favours of his Wyfe, the right thereof did return to the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, albeit he ſuffered his Wife to poſſeſs the renunced Lands all her life time, yet the extant product of theſe Lands did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to him, and that he himſelf could not be excluded by the perſonal objection of his own Renounciation.</hi> The like was found in the caſe of <hi>Hamilton</hi> againſt the Lady <hi>Carberry.</hi> And, if the Husband could not by a <hi>Direct deed</hi> renounce the <hi>unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counntable management,</hi> much leſs can he do it by a <hi>general and ſeparate</hi> Clauſe, which would in conſequence import a renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation
<pb facs="tcp:42385:22"/>thereof to his Wife, for the <hi>Jus mariti,</hi> conſiſts not only in the <hi>Management,</hi> but it muſt be <hi>unaccountable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3, <hi>Et Separatim,</hi> the Defender cannot be lyable <hi>In quantum Lucratus,</hi> upon this Clauſe, tho' it could be effectual in Law, unleſs it were ſubſumed and offered to be proven, that he was <hi>Lucratus, by applying ſums of money received during the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to the payment of his Debts.</hi> For albeit it were inſtructed that the Defunct did receive conſiderable ſums of Money, and alſo that he payed conſiderable ſums due by him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet that could not infer that theſe debts were payed by ſums of Money receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed during the Marriage, ſeing the Defunct had <hi>another Subject</hi> than <hi>Sums of Money,</hi> out of which he could have payed his Debts <hi>viz</hi> 24. <hi>Chalders</hi> of <hi>Victual</hi> yearly as a part of the Purſuers Joynture, which in the debate is acknowledged to have been allocat for the Defuncts free diſpoſal at his pleaſure. Suppoſe then that the Defunct had conſumed his Sallaries, and Penſions, upon the charges and expenſes of his Family, or upon other reaſonable and creditable occaſions (as it is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged he might have done freely and unaccountably) and that he were <hi>Lucratus</hi> by applying the ſaids 24. <hi>Chalders</hi> of Victual for the payment of his Debt; he could not be ſaid to be <hi>Lucratus</hi> by <hi>ſums</hi> of Money, but only by Bolls of Victual, for which, by the clauſe he is not accountable; and if the Purſuer will aſſert that he is <hi>Lucratus</hi> by <hi>ſums</hi> of Money <hi>Aſſerenti incumbit probatio.</hi> And farther he had other ſubjects out of which payments might be made, <hi>viz.</hi> The Lands of <hi>Collingtoun</hi> which were ſtocked, as alſo he ſold 100000. <hi>Merks</hi> worth of <hi>Lands,</hi> and there is nothing more ordinary, than, for overburdened Heritours to obtaine great eaſes, when they have ready money to pay, whereby the ſaid 100000. <hi>Merks</hi> may have payed 100000 <hi>pounds</hi> of debt, So that my Lady cannot be exonered upon a <hi>preſumptive,</hi> but muſt adduce a poſitive probation, that my Lord was <hi>Lucratus by ſums of Money.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 The Purſuer muſt not only prove, that the Defunct was once <hi>Lucratus by payment of his Debt,</hi> but that the ſaid <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crum did remaine with him, till the diſſolution of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:42385:22"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> purging any of the Debts, did upon a juſt and reaſonable cauſe, diſpoſe of his <hi>releived Lands</hi> to his eldeſt Son by Contract of Marriage, as is alledg'd, the Purſuer cannot claim any intereſt in that purchaſs; But it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears evidently by the Contract, that the Defender was then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to ſuceced to his Father in theſe <hi>Lands,</hi> in ſo far as the very Clauſe upon which the Purſuer founds her <hi>conqueſce to be provided to her in lyfrent, and the Bairns of the Marriage in fee, which failing to the</hi> Defuncts <hi>other Heirs appointed to ſucceed him, in his other Lands and Estate;</hi> whereby it appears, that as the Defender was the lineal Legal Succeſſor of his Father, the Purſuer did not then envy his ſucceſſion to the Eſtate of <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingtoun,</hi> which by her own clauſe of <hi>Conqueſce,</hi> is deſigned <hi>his other Lands</hi> and <hi>Eſtate;</hi> ſo that the Lands of <hi>Collingtoun</hi> can never be reckoned Conqueſce; nor can the Purſuer quarel the convoying the right therof to the Defender, ſeing by her own Contract, it is declared that his <hi>preſent Lands and Estate not contracted was deſigned to deſcend to his Lineal Heirs</hi> which could not be, unleſs it had been alſo Lawful to purge the ſame of Debts, being then burdened above the value, and as it was arbitrary to the Defunct not to have made any <hi>Purchaſe,</hi> ſo he might juſtly diſpoſe of it: But that the Lords may be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed how Calumnious, and groundleſs this great noiſe of <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe</hi> is, they would be informed, that the Defender being Married in <hi>Anno.</hi> 1670. Within a few years after the Contract, it was not poſſible the Defunct could make any purchaſe before the Defenders Marriage; Becauſe all the Subject of his Eſtate was my Ladies Joynture of 36. <hi>Chalders</hi> of Victual, 200 <hi>pounds</hi> Sterling of Sallary, and the Lands of <hi>Collingtoun</hi> not then exceeding 3000 <hi>Merks;</hi> out of this, he had all the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary charges of his Family, Servants, Coach, and Horſes to lay out, and the Defender to intertain in his travels, and the Annual-rent of his weighty debt to pay, after which deductions there will remaine no place for Conqueſce: And after the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender was Married, he lived in that intire Confidence with his Father, that all the portion he received, which was known to
<pb facs="tcp:42385:23"/>be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> by his Father to him, was as much poſſeſt and enjoyed by his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as by himſelfe, never having heard of this pretence of <hi>Conqueſce,</hi> and looking upon his Fathers intereſt and his own, as the ſame, many ſums affecting the Eſtate were payed by him without ſo much as mention from whom the money was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and there were no Aſſignations taken to any Debt, but alwayes Renounciations and Diſcharges; ſo that if this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous pretence ſhould hold foot, my <hi>Lady</hi> ſhould lyfrent the Defenders portion, which was four times greater then the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſce, it being impoſſible to diſtinguiſh the one from the other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In reſpect whereof,</hi> the <hi>Lords,</hi> are humbly intreated to give diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct interloquitors upon the ſeveral grounds abovemention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and particularly, 1 Anent the <hi>Extent</hi> and <hi>Import</hi> of the clauſe of <hi>Conqueſce</hi> 2 Anent the <hi>Import</hi> of the ſecond clauſe, if it does relate to ſums <hi>due</hi> or <hi>falling due</hi> after rhe Marriage. 3 If the ſame could be of any greater force than a clauſe of <hi>Conqueſce</hi> tho' it did relate to ſums due <hi>after</hi> the Marriage. 4 If by ſuch a conſtruction the ſecond clauſe would not be equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent to a <hi>Renounciation</hi> of the <hi>Jus mariti,</hi> as to theſe ſums in favours of the Wife, and if ſuch a <hi>Renounciation</hi> can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt with <hi>Law</hi> and former <hi>Deciſions.</hi> 5 If the Purſuers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the payment of Debts, and the receiving of ſums of Money, could infer a ſufficient <hi>evidente</hi> that theſe Debts were payed by the ſums of Money, ſeing there were other <hi>Subjects</hi> out of which the Debts might have been payed. 6 If the Defunct can be reckoned <hi>Lucratus,</hi> ſeing he did not <hi>Die in the fee</hi> of theſe Lands releived, but was denuded there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of upon a moſt juſt and rational account, <hi>ſine fraude,</hi> which are all diſtinct grounds ſeparatly proponed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:42385:23"/>
               <head>A Liſt of the <hi>Deciſions</hi> related to in the Lord <hi>Collingtoun's</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, againſt the Lady <hi>Caſtle-haven.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat the Husband hath the abſolute Adminiſtration and Managment of all Rents, Annual-rents, and other Moveables, belonging to his Wife during the Marriage; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding any Renounciation of his <hi>Jus Mariti</hi> thereto, in Favours of the Wife, is evident from theſe following De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">9 <hi>February</hi> 1667. <hi>Lady</hi> Colling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toun <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Lord</hi> Colling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toun.</note>The <hi>Lords</hi> found, that the Clauſe in my Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi>'s Contract, renouncing his <hi>jus mariti</hi> in favours of his Lady, did not debar my Lord from the management, and adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Rents deſtinate for maintenance of the Family; and that albeit the adminiſtration and management had been expreſly renounced by him in the ſaid Contract: The ſaid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounciation had been <hi>contra bonos mores,</hi> and ſo void and null in Law; and that the Husbands adminiſtration being the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent Right and Priviledge of the Husband as ſuch, was ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute and unaccountable, and could not be renounced in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of the Wife.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">13 July 1678. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colſon <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra</hi> Inglis.</note>The <hi>Lords</hi> found, that a Wife having in her Contract of Marriage reſerved a Power to diſpoſe upon her Liferent with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Husbands conſent, and the Husband having renounced his <hi>jus mariti</hi> to what was ſo reſerved: The ſaid renounciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did recurre and accreſs to the Husband himſelf by the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; and after Deceaſe of the Husband, allowed Compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation to the Heirs of the Husband, againſt the Wife and her Aſſigney, upon the account of the Wiſes intromiſſion <hi>Stante Matrimonio,</hi> with the Rents ſo reſerved, and whereof the <hi>jus mariti</hi> was renounced, as ſaid is.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2</hi> February <hi>1667.</hi> Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors of the Lady <hi>Pilton</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra <hi>Hay</hi> of <hi>Balhouſie.</hi>
                  </note>The Laird of <hi>Balhouſie</hi> having granted Bond to his Wifes Siſter the Lady <hi>Pilton</hi> for 1000 Merks yearly, to be imployed by her for any uſe ſhe pleaſed. without her Husbands conſent, and ſecluding his <hi>jus mariti;</hi> The <hi>Lords</hi> found, payment made to the Husband ſufficient to Aſſolȝie from a purſute upon a
<pb facs="tcp:42385:24"/>Bond, notwithſtanding that by the Bond it ſelf, the Husbands <hi>jus Mariti</hi> was excluded.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A liſt of <hi>Deciſions</hi> anent the Import and extent of Clauſes of Proviſion in Contracts of Marriage, conceived in Favours of Heirs of Conqueſce and Proviſion, and Bairns of ſecond Marriages; for clearing, that notwithſtanding ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, and Obligments, the Husband, or Father, hath the abſolute Power and Dominion and unaccountable Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Conqueſce.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Lords</hi> ſound an gratuitous Bond granted by <hi>Thomas Cowan,</hi> to the Daughter of his firſt Marriage, long after his ſecond Contract of Marriage, whereby he was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to provide all his ſubſequent Conqueſce to the Heirs of that ſecond Marriage, to affect his Conqueſce during the ſaid ſecond Marriage:<note place="margin">9 February 1669 <hi>Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> contra <hi>Young.</hi>
                  </note> Notwithſtanding that the Daughter of the firſt Marriage, to whom the gratuitous Bond was granted, was both foris-familiat, and <hi>aliunde</hi> ſufficiently provided before that time; and it appears by the debate, that as a Husband might freely have gifted all his Conqueſt to Strangers, ſo he might likewayes gift rational proportions thereof to his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of former Marriages, notwithſtanding any ſuch obligment in his ſecond Contract.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Lords</hi> found, that the Obligments and Proviſions for Conqueſce in Contracts of Matriage, did not hinder the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracters to diſpone thereupon during their Lifetime:<note place="margin">16 June 1676, <hi>Mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel</hi> contra <hi>The Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of</hi> Thomas Little-john</note> And that all reaſonable Deeds, albeit they were done or granted, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out equivalent onerous Cauſes, were effectual, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch Obligements and Proviſions of Conqueſce; and that the Children in whoſe favours the ſaids Obligements of Conqueſce were conceived, could not be heard to quarrel the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">19 June <hi>Murray</hi>'s contra <hi>Murray</hi>'s.</note>The <hi>Lords</hi> found, that rational Proviſions to Children of a prior Marriage; could not be quarrelled upon the Clauſe of Conqueſce in the Fathers ſecond Contract of Marriage: And
<pb facs="tcp:42385:24"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 7000 Merks granted to the eldeſt Son of the firſt Marriage: Notwithſtanding that the eldeſt Son, had ſucceeded to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Land Eſtate by his Father: And in that <hi>Deciſion</hi> the <hi>Lords</hi> declared, that they would make the former <hi>Deciſion, Mitchel, contra,</hi> the Children of <hi>Little-John,</hi> a Rule for the future.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Lords</hi> found that old <hi>Niddry</hi> having applied conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſums for acquiring in new and preferrable Rights of the Lands of <hi>Lochtour,</hi> and for purging and disburdening the Lands, of other Incumbrances and Debts: The ſums ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended during his ſecond Marriage could not be repute as ſums Conqueſt during that Marriage;<note place="margin">19 Februa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry 1683. <hi>James Wanchop</hi> contra Laird of <hi>Niddrie.</hi>
                  </note> in reſpect <hi>Niddry</hi> had a right to the ſaids Lands of <hi>Lochtour,</hi> ſtanding in his Perſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that time: And found that <hi>James Wauchop</hi> as Heir of the ſecond Marriage could have no Intereſt in the ſaids new ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired Rights, or for repetition of the ſums expended for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring the ſame, upon the Obligment in his Mothers Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of Marriage, for providing all the Conqueſce to him: And this demonſtrates, that ſums expended for disburdening a mans <hi>Prior</hi> Heretage, of Debts and Incumbrances affecting the ſame, can never be repute <hi>Conqueſce,</hi> albeit thereby the Eſtate be nottourly meliorat and improven, and the yearly Rent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in to the man augmented.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Liſt of <hi>Deciſions</hi> for clearing the import, and extent of Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligments and Proviſions of Conqueſt, conceived in Favours of Wives, as to their Liferents.</head>
               <p>The <hi>Lords</hi> found, that albeit the Husband was obliged to provide the hail ſums acquired during the Marriage, in favours of his Wife in Liferent; yet a Bond taken by a Husband pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to a Child of his former Marriage,<note place="margin">10 <hi>Febru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary</hi> 1629, <hi>Oliphant</hi> contra <hi>Phinnit.</hi>
                  </note> did not fall under the Obligment of Conqueſce; and found, that Conqueſce was only to be underſtood of what was ſtanding in the perſon of the Husband, and undiſpoſed of, the time of his Deceaſe:</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:42385:25"/>
               <p>The <hi>Lords</hi> found, that a Husband having, <hi>Stante Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monio,</hi> acquired the property of Lands, formerly holding of himſelf;<note place="margin">26 <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> 1629. Lady <hi>Dum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fermling</hi> contra Earl of <hi>Dumferm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</hi>
                  </note> and thereafter before his Deceaſe, diſponing the ſame to be like wayes holden of himſelf, for a double or triple <hi>Few-Duty;</hi> That neither the ſaid Acquiſition nor Improvement, by tripling the <hi>Few-Duty,</hi> did fall under the Obligment of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſce in the Wife's Contract of Marriage, albeit the ſame was acquired, and improven in her time; In reſpect the Earl had a Right to theſe Lands <hi>Prior</hi> to the Marriage, albeit the ſame was only a Right of Superiority.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">15 <hi>July</hi> 1673. <hi>Robertſon</hi> contra <hi>Robertſon.</hi>
                  </note>The <hi>Lords</hi> found, that an obligement for providing the Wife to all the Conqueſce, could not hinder the Father to grant proviſions to his Children of a former Marriage, and even to the eldeſt Son and appear and Heir.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander Frazer</hi> having in his contract of Marriage with <hi>Chriſtian Frazer</hi> his ſecond Wife, provided her to a mean Proviſion of the annual rent of 3400 Merks, and to the lyfrent of the half of the Conqueſt that ſhould be made during the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and having for preventing any debate anent the Conqueſt inſert in the ſaid contract,<note place="margin">8 <hi>December</hi> 1687 <hi>Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer</hi> contra <hi>Frazer.</hi>
                  </note> a particular inventar of his Eſtate, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to 11000 pounds ſcots or thereby. It happened there was a conſiderable Conqueſce of 15 or 16000 pounds, made during that Marriage, But <hi>Alexander Frazer</hi> the Husband, did exhauſt and ſpend all the ſaid conqueſce by gratuitous Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations to his eldeſt Son and Daughter of the firſt Marriage, of 8000 pounds, Scots, and upwards, and did expend the ſum of other 8000 pounds, or thereby, that was likwayes acquir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed during that Marriage, for payment of other Debts, for which he was engadged <hi>Prior</hi> to his ſaid ſecond Contract.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſtian Frazer,</hi> having after the deceaſe of the ſaid Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander, purſued his Heir, for the half of the foreſaid Conqueſce: and it being debated, whether the gratuit ous donations to the Children of the firſt Marriage, and the ſums payed out for Debts contracted and due by the Husband before his entring into the ſecond contract of Marriage with the Purſuer, ſhould affect the Eſtate belonging to the Husband before that Contract and
<pb facs="tcp:42385:25"/>the ſaids gratuitous Donations and Debts ſua payed, ſhould be ſuſtained to exhauſt the Conqueſce, in prejudice of the Relicts Lyfrent, who was ſo meanly provided. <hi>The Lords found that the Heir of the Defunct, ought to have the</hi> 11000 <hi>pound to which the Fathers Eſtate was eſtimate in the ſaid ſecond Contract, allowed and made free to him, in the firſt place, and that the haill debts due by the Husband when he died, whether contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before, or after the ſecond contract of Marriage, ought to be payed, and affect the Conqueſce in the Second place and that the Relict could only have right to the half of the ſuperplus of the Conqueſce</hi> (if any was) <hi>after the two Deductions above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is obſervable, that albeit there were two Bills given in craving the ſaid interloquitor to be rectified upon thir grounds, 1 That a conſiderable part of the 11000 pounds, to which the Husbands Eſtate was eſtimat, was exhauſled by payment of Debts due before the ſecond Contract, and 2 That the 4000 pounds gifted by the Defunct to his oun Heire of Line, who was obliged to <hi>Implement</hi> the Fathers obligment anent the Wifes lyfrent, might at leaſt be ſuſtained as Conqueſce. <hi>Both bills were refuſed, and the firſt interloquitor adhered to;</hi> So that the Husbands Eſtate which was once for the moſt part exhauſted by the foreſaid gratuitous Donations, and antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Debts, as ſaid is, immediately after the ſecond Marriage, and before any Conqueſce could be made, was Suſtained to be made up, to the Heir out of the Subſequent Conqueſce, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out allowing the Relict her lyfrent of the equal half thereof, conform to the obligments of the Contract, albeit her other proviſions were ſo mean and inconſiderable, And the principal decreet is produced marked with ſeveral letters of the Alphabet, directing to the grounds therein pleaded, and determined and herein repeated, and the ſorſaid <hi>Deciſion</hi> was ſo ſolemn, that the <hi>Lords</hi> declared to the Procurators on both ſides Judicialy, that they would obſerve the ſaid <hi>Deciſion</hi> in all ſuch caſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:42385:26"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">20 <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> 1665. <hi>Laird of</hi> Kilbocho <hi>contra La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> Kilbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho.</note>The <hi>Lords</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd, that a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> was obliged to pay me an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual-rents of the price of Conqueſt Lands. notwithſtanding that ſhe was provided Simply and abſolutly to the Conqueſce, and that the Heir was ſufficiently able to have payed the ſame. And by this <hi>Deciſion,</hi> as alſo by an other <hi>Deciſion</hi> betwixt the Earls of <hi>Dumfermling</hi> and <hi>Callendar,</hi> The Practick alledged upon by the Purſuer in the caſe of the Counteſs of <hi>Dumfermling</hi> in <hi>Anno.</hi> 1625 is fully anſwered, and elided.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE INTERLOQUITOR, <hi>Edinburgh</hi> 29 <hi>January</hi> 1690.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Lords</hi> having adviſed the debate, <hi>Finds,</hi> that the <hi>clauſe of Conqueſce</hi> lybelled, did not hinder the deceaſed Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> to ſpend his yearly revenue as he thought fit. And <hi>find,</hi> that the Lady, be vertue of the clauſes in the Contract; has right to the Lyfrent of all ſums, which belonged to him the time of his entering into the ſecond Marriage, or the time of his deceaſe. But they <hi>find,</hi> that albeit it were cleare that he had releived his <hi>old Lands</hi> and <hi>Estate,</hi> of Debts, which affected the ſame, the time of his entering into the ſecond Marriage, by ſums acquired during the ſecond Marriage; Yet that the Lady by no clauſe in the contract, has any right to purſue for the lyfrent of the Lands releived by ſuch ſums. And that the Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> might have imployed the ſums ſo acquired; for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving his Eſtate of Debts affecting the ſame the time of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering into his ſecond Marriage, Notwithſtanding of any clauſe in the Contract.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Sic Subſcribitur</hi> JAMES DALRYMPLE. I.P.D.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="appeal">
               <pb facs="tcp:42385:26"/>
               <head>The Ladies Appeal and Protestation</head>
               <p>I Dame <hi>Margaret Areskine</hi> Lady <hi>Caſtle haven,</hi> Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that in the Proceſs purſued at my Inſtance before the Lords of Seſſion, againſt Sir <hi>James Foulis</hi> now of <hi>Colling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toun:</hi> The ſaids Lords be their Interloquitor bearing date the 29 of <hi>January</hi> inſtant, Found that the <hi>Clauſe of Conqueſce</hi> Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled, did not hinder the Deceaſt Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> to ſpend his yearly Revenue as he thought fit: And found that the Lady be vertue of the Clauſes in the Contract, has right to the Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of all ſums which belonged to him the time of his entering into the ſecond Marriage, or the time of his Deceaſe: But they found, that albeit it were clear that he had reliev'd his <hi>old Lands,</hi> and <hi>Eſtate,</hi> of Debts which affected the ſame the time of his entring into the ſecond Marriage, by ſums acquired during the ſecond Marriage; yet that the Lady by no Clauſe in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract has any Right to purſue for the Liferent of the <hi>Lands re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved</hi> by ſuch ſums; and that the Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi> might have imployed the ſums ſo acquited, for relieving his Eſtate of Debts affecting the ſame, the time of entering into his ſecond Marriage, notwithſtanding of any clauſe in the Contract: By which Interloquitor I conceive my ſelf prejudged; and that by the <hi>Claim of Right</hi> it is provided, That any perſon ſo prejudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, may appeal for <hi>remeed of Law</hi> to an higher Judicature, I do therefore by thir preſents. Appeal and proteſt from the ſaids <hi>Lords of Seſſion,</hi> to the <hi>High Court of Parliament</hi> for remeed of Law as ſaid is, and intreats your Lordſhips to ſtop the ſaid <hi>Interloquitor</hi> till it be heard in Parliament <hi>Sic ſubſcribitur</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. ARESKINE,</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <pb facs="tcp:42385:27"/>
               <head>The Ladies Petition to the Parliament.</head>
               <opener>Unto His Grace His Majeſties high <hi>Commiſſioner,</hi> And to the Right Honourable the <hi>Nobles,</hi> and <hi>Barrons,</hi> and <hi>Burgeſſes,</hi> Aſſembled in <hi>Parliament. Dame</hi> Margaret Areskine, <hi>Lady</hi> Caſtle-haven: HUMBLY SHEWETH,</opener>
               <p>THat the late Sir <hi>James Foulis</hi> of <hi>Collingtoun</hi> having long ſought your Petitioner in Marriage, did offer his Houſe and Yards, and 3000: Merks be Year, to me in Jointure: Which he conſeſt was all he had. Your Petitioner having at laſt conſented to Marry, but did refuſe to take the 3000 Merks: Since it was cleare that his Children in his firſt Marriage by his firſt Lady, ſhould then want altogether; Yet he ſaid, though they ſhould want he would ſecure me in that. But when I told him, I would not deale ſo with his Children, but Condeſcended to accept of his Houſe and Yards, and the Life rent of all Sums of Money, Bands, or Heretage, which he ſhould Conqueſs or acquire, and of all ſums of Money due to him, which he ſhall happen to receive during the ſaid Marriage. And he obliges himſelf to Employ the ſame, and take the Rights thereof to himſelf and Your Petitioner, the longeſt liver of us two in Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent: Of this he was ſo well pleaſed, that he deſired it might be ſecured as my Lawyers ſhould deſire, which was accordingly done in as expreſs Terms as they thought poſſible, upon this Marriage following. And what ever proviſion was made in the Petitioners Favours, in that Contract, as to my own for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Eſtate: Yet he poſſeſſed and employed a conſiderable part of my Eſtate, to entertaine his Sons Family, and to pay his former Debt After his Deceaſe, your Petitioner little doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Poſſeſſion of what was ſo fairly Contracted; But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forced to Suit it before the now Lords of Seſſion. They by their <hi>Interloquitor</hi> of the 29th of <hi>January</hi> laſt, Did Find, <hi>That the clauſe of the Contract did not hinder the Lord</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingtoun
<pb facs="tcp:42385:27"/>
                  <hi>to Employ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ms he acquired during the ſecond Marriage for payment of the Debt, before he entered in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Marriage.</hi> Though this be expreſly contrary to the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Faith of the ſecond Contract, by which he is expreſly bound to Employ all Sums he ſhould Acquire, ſo as your Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner might Life-rent them. But leaſt the <hi>Iniquity</hi> deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhould not be cleare enough, ſince no clauſe in the Contract could prejudge his Creditors, or hinder them to affect theſe new Acquired Sums. The ſaids Lords by another Clauſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared that if he Employed his Money to pay his Debt, and ſo to relieve Lands formerly morgaged by him to Creditors yet that your Petitioner by no means could pretend to the Rent of theſe Lands ſo redeemed by the Money, which by the Faith of the Contract, was deſtinate for your Petitioner; by which <hi>ſtrange Sentence</hi> all Faith of Contracts is violated, and Law which ſhould protect Widdows is wreſted, to their Ruine and Fraud, and indirect Dealings is not only Encouraged, but owned to be the Deſign of the Law; for whatever might be pretended for employing the Money acquired during the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, for releiving his morgadged Eſtate, yet what can colour the Fraud and Iniquitie of employing it ſo contrary to the Tenour and expreſs Faith of the Contract, and the Equity of the Conveyance, as to force the profite of that Money to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend on the Lord <hi>Collingtoun</hi>'s Son, in Defraud of his Wife, by whom he profited conſiderably, and Conſequently was as onerous, and Juſt a Creditor, as he had or could have. This being ſo clearly to Impugne Law, Equity, Juſtice, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, that none who knew the late Lord <hi>Collingtoun,</hi> thinks he deſigned ſo foul a Fraud; nor could ever ſuch an Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Contract fall under the Proſpect of ſo Honeſt a Man. Albeit your Petitioners Lawyers did fully Redargue all theſe Quibbles, which my Oppoſites Propond, and that all Lawyers who were not Blinded with Perſonal concern, doe look on this Sentence alike oppoſite to Law, as to Equity, and the Intereſt of Mankind: Yet no Addreſs to the greateſt part of theſe Judges would procure Redreſs or Delay to your
<pb facs="tcp:42385:28"/>Petitioner, whereupon I was permitted (though with Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty) to appeal to His Majeſty, and his Parliament as the laſt Reſult and great Sanctuary of the Injured, and Oppreſt: That your Grace, and Lordſhips, who ſits in the higheſt Capacity of Law, ſhould have Occaſion to Vindicate the Kings Laws from the ſtaine of being a covering for Fraud, on Subtil, or Wreſted Notions. And to ſhew the Nation that Faith, Truth, and Honeſty, are what Law is appointed to Suſtaine, and to let the People find the Judgement of the Nation, can diſcern Equity from Fraud, and is the beſt and laſt Refuge to the Injur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; Your Petitioners Appeal in this Matter being given in the 31 <hi>January</hi> laſt, it could not procure ſo much as Delay, but Decreet was given out,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>MAY IT THEREFORE PLEASE YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R GRACE, and</hi> Lordſhips, <hi>to grant warrand to Cite the Lord</hi> Collingtoun, <hi>or any others ye ſhall think fit, to Compeare before Your</hi> GRACE <hi>and</hi> Lordſhips, <hi>on</hi> 24 <hi>Houres Warning, he being a Member of your Meeting; and to call for the proceſs, and Appeal, and to Judge therein as ſeems Good and Just: And in this ſmall Caſe, to ſhew the Nation, what ſafety they have in their own Repreſentatives, when called by His Majeſties Sacred Authority, and what differences there is by Judging according to Equity, and expreſs meaning of Parties, and Judging by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nthought of Subtilties. And Humbly BEGGS, That the Tenour of the Contract be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in the plain Senſe, and juſt effect; And Decern the Lord</hi> Collingtoun <hi>to pay the Petitioner, the Intereſt of what Money his Father received during the Marriage, belonging to him, and that for all Years ſince his Fathers Death, and in time coming, during the Petitioners Life; And to remit to the</hi> Lords of Seſſion <hi>to receive what probation Your Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner ſhall adduce, for proving what Money his Father did receive belonging to him during the Marriage, and that they may give therein Decreet accordingly, And Your Petitioner ſhall ever Pray,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:42385:28"/>
               <p>IF the Members of Parliament, or any other perſons ſhall be pleaſed to peruſe the above-written Proceſs; they may have a much ſurer ground to found their Judgment and Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination upon, in this Caſe, (which is important to the Parties, but more in the preparative to the Kingdom) Than to rely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the bare aſſertion of either Party.</p>
               <p>It is no new thing that Parties ſhould be perſwaded of the Iniquity of any Sentence, which cuts them off, from their Hopes and Expectations; and that Complaints and Murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings ſhould ariſe upon theſe Sentences, which alwayes were, and may be expected; and therefore, it was ever the care of our Law-givers, that neither the Judicatures, nor the Perſons of our Judges ſhould be Vilified or Contemned, ſeing they Repreſent the Kings Perſon, in the Adminiſtration of Juſtice: Nor that the Judges ſhould be allowed to abuſe the Authority that is committed to them, by doing Wrong or Unhoneſty. Therefore ſhortly after the Inſtitution of the Colledge of Juſtice, it is provided by the 68 Act. 5. Parl. <hi>Ja.</hi> 5. <hi>That the Lords of Seſſion ſhould be had in ſpecial Honour, and that no Credit be had to any that Murmur againſt them: But they ſhall be called b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fore the King, and if they be found Culpable, they ſhall be puniſhed after the quality of their fault; and if they be found Clean and Innocent; the Perſon complaining ſhall be puniſhed with rigour, and never have Credit with the King. again.</hi> This Statute and all others, in relation to the Seſſion are yet ſtanding Laws, and are ſutable and agreable to that Article in the Inſtrument of Government. <hi>Whereby it is provided, That it is the Right and Priviledge of the Subject, to proteſt for remeed of Law to the King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, againſt Sentences pronounced by the Lords of Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> Which doth not Authorize every Proteſtation at the pleaſure of the Party; but only in theſe Caſes, wherein Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murs and Complaints were allowed by our Antient Laws: And if ſuch Proteſtarions be now found Injurious, the Party pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting,
<pb facs="tcp:42385:29"/>is puniſhable by the former ſtanding Law, againſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Murmurers and Complainers</p>
               <p>No Proteſtation for remeed of Law having formerly occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſince the <hi>Claime of Right,</hi> it is of the greateſt importancy, that the extent and meaning of the ſaid Article of the <hi>Meeting of Estates</hi> be carefully and narrowly conſidered, that no practice follow upon it, which might tend to render the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y and poſſeſſion of the Subject more Doubtful, Diſquiet, and Unſecure, than formerly, contrary to the cleare deſigne thereof; By which it was intended, <hi>That an important right and priviledge of the Subject ſhould be aſſerted and declared.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the firſt place then, the foreſaid Declaration does not Warrant, nor Authorize Appeals, but only Proteſtations for remeed of Law. On the contrary, the ſame doth clearly Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port a Prohibition of Appeals, by the laſt Proviſion thereof, <hi>That ſuch Proteſtations ſhall not ſtop the Execution of the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of the Lords.</hi> Which is equivalent, as if the <hi>Meeting</hi> of <hi>Eſtates</hi> had expreſly diſcharged Appeals, ſeing the plain Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of an Appeal, is to ſuſpend all effect of the Deciſion or Interloquitor of that Judge, from whom the party Appeals; yet the Lady thought fit to preſent a Paper, Appealing from the Lords: And in her Petition, ſhe doth not deſign the Paper preſented by her <hi>a Proteſtation,</hi> but an <hi>Appeal,</hi> which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated in three ſeveral places of that Petition: Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Appeals be expreſly prohibited and the Lords of Seſſion Impowered, <hi>To decide utterly in civil Cauſes purſued before them, without remeed of Appellation to King and Parliament,</hi> by the 62 <hi>Act.</hi> 14 <hi>Parl.</hi> King <hi>Jam.</hi> 2. And the 39 <hi>Act.</hi> 5. <hi>Parl. Ja</hi> 5. And which Acts were not Intended to be Abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate or Reſcinded by any Article in the Claim of Right.</p>
               <p n="2">2 It cannot be imagined that the <hi>Meeting of Estates,</hi> did intend that a party might freely proteſt for remeed of Law in every ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe, without any hazard or inconvenience, In caſe that Prote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tation were found not to proceed on juſt g ounds, for the ſaid Article be ng no conſtitution of any new Right not formerly competent to the Subjects, But an aſſertion and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calaration
<pb facs="tcp:42385:29"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap> be meaſured by our ancient Laws, which did allow murmurings and complaints upon juſt grounds; in the ſame caſes Proteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations are allowed by that Article, as if the Lords ſhould refuſe to Miniſter Juſtice, or if they ſhould not only be Judges, but Soliſters, partial Counſellers, Aſſiſters and Partakers with ſome of the parties, and to take Geir and Profite; in theſe caſes, as Murmurs and Complaints were Lawful be the 26, act 5 <hi>par. Ja.</hi> 3. and 104 <hi>Act. Par.</hi> 7. <hi>Ja.</hi> 5. So are Proteſtations for remeed of Law: Or if the Seſſion being a limited Judicatory, ſhould proceed to decide in matters not falling under their Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, As in matters of State and Government, or Crimes; or ſuſtaine themſelves Judges in the firſt inſtance in adjudica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Prizes, or Divorces. As likewayes, if the <hi>Lords</hi> ſhould upon full debate decide, and thereafter upon the ſame grounds formerly repreſented <hi>ſuper iiſdem deductis,</hi> ſhould retract that, and make a direct contrary <hi>Deciſion,</hi> whereby parties would alwayes be uncertaine of their Rights. For if they might once retract their <hi>Deciſion</hi> on the ſame grounds, they might doe it againe and againe for ever; and the great Inconveniency of this was diſcovered by our Predeceſſors many ages agoe, for evit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whereof by the foreſaid 62 <hi>Act</hi> 14. <hi>Par. Ja.</hi> 2. All Cauſes were appointed to be utterly decided by the Lords of Seſſion, but any remeed by appellation to King or Parliament, becauſe if appeals were once allowed, it were impoſſible to bound the Parliament, or terminate any <hi>Deciſion;</hi> for the Parliament hath alwayes power to reſcind any Law that could limite them, and make contrary <hi>Deciſions</hi> on the ſame grounds as oft as they pleaſed, without any Imaginable remeed. In all theſe caſes abovementioned, Complaints and Proteſtations are lawful, but ſtill with the Caution and Limitation mentioned in out ancient Laws and Acts of Parliament. <hi>viz, That if Murmurs, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, or Proteſtations be interpoſed without Just and Legal Grounds authorized by the Law, the Preſenters thereof are ſeverely puniſhable;</hi> which is moſt neceſſary for preſerving the Honour and Reſpect of the <hi>Supreme ordinary Iudicature,</hi> which
<pb facs="tcp:42385:30"/>bears <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>As this is plain reaſon upon the one hand, ſo let the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence be conſidered on the other: For if ſuch Proteſtations were allowed to be offered at the pleaſure of any Party, they would neceſſarily come to proceed of courſe, and none who have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Diſadvantage by the <hi>Deciſion,</hi> will fail to offer a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, which doth not coſt one Farthing of Charge; and whereby there may remain an hope and expectation, that one day, they may have that Sentence reverſed; for few men can be ſo juſt and equal in their own Concerns, as to be eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the Juſtice of a <hi>Deciſion,</hi> which cuts off their Claim, or makes them lyable to great Burdens or Debts: And that after great loſs of Labour, Time and Money; and of thoſe that can be convinced, there are many who will not have the Ingenuity to forbear interpoſing any Proteſtation, that may ſupport the Intereſt of their Cauſe, right or wrong.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Suppoſe then this Inevitable Conſequence, that every decreet did containe in the Boſom of it, a proteſtation <hi>for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcinding thereof by the King in Parliament;</hi> with what aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance or quiet, could any man enjoy his fortune, which at any time had been called in queſtion, or might become debat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in any time by paſt, or to come? How ſhould any man know to regulate himſelf in the expence of his Living, the edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation or proviſion of his Children, or in the Management of any of his Affairs? For ſuppoſe the uſual wayes of Inhibition, Arreiſtment, or other Diligence upon the grounds of any proceſs had been uſed, and that the Judge ordinary had annul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all upon payment, or other ground of Law, yet the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Proteſtation would ſo fetter that party who was once under diligence, that to the end of the World, he could not diſpoſe upon any part of his Eſtate heretable or moveable, that was at any time under Diligence; becauſe, if that Sentence of the Lords, by which the diligence was found extinct, ſhould come to be reduced, the diligence would revive. And all Acquir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for whatever cauſe, become lyable to reſtitution, and tho' it came never to be reverſed, yet the poſſibility thereof would
<pb facs="tcp:42385:30"/>ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap> burdened, nor diſpoſe of any part of his Eſtate for payment of his other Debts.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is the aim and Intention of the Law of all Nations, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t aliquis tandem ſit finis litium:</hi> And therefore every Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath their ſeveral forms of <hi>Proceſs,</hi> to which every party muſt comply: And very often, it falls out in every Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that thoſe who have really and truly material Juſtice on their part, do juſtly ſuccumb in their Cauſe for neglect of theſe Forms; for whom the Law provides no remedy, but only gives them warning of their danger, and tells them, <hi>Vigilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, non dormientibus, jura ſubveniunt;</hi> Other Caſes again are ſo dubious, that upon full debate, the Judges and Learned Lawyers of every Nation, are divided in their Opinions; ſo that the <hi>Deciſions</hi> of moſt Important Cauſes are often carried but by one or two Votes, (tho' it was far otherwayes in this Caſe) Yet it is generally thought every where, more ſecure, to reſt in the <hi>Deciſion</hi> of the moſt doubtful Caſe, than to leave parties unſettled in their Rights and poſſeſſions: And oft-times it happens, that through the diſadvantage of Indiſtinct and unclear repreſentation of Caſes, the ſame Judge may deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine otherwayes, then he would have done, if the Caſe had been fully and clearly repreſented: And frequently points are mentioned in Debates ſo overly, that they are neither noticed nor regarded by the oppoſite Advocats, nor the Lords at de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciding; and yet being once mentioned, they would be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent in a Review, where being Illuſtrate, they might appear more important, than all that was debated, or under conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration at the time of the <hi>Deciſion;</hi> and ſo might be a ground to annul what was done moſt juſtly upon the grounds urged, and under Conſideration, whereby the Juſtice and Integrity of the Lords might be tarniſhed by the Faults and Omiſſions of Parties or Procurators. And if by Proteſtations ſuch doubtful Caſes were brought in without limitation, to be debated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a different Judicatory proceeding by different forms, and in a diſtinct view and in another light; it were impoſſible for
<pb facs="tcp:42385:31"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap> a debate, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> what might be t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>equences o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a contrary <hi>Deciſion,</hi> to hundreds of Third parties, who had no Intereſt or concern the time of the firſt Sentence. Nor can any perſon foreſee all that might follow upon ſuch a ſudden alteration, as to allow <hi>unlimited Proteſtations</hi> in any Caſe; only this much is plain, that the evident evil Conſequences are ſo many, as would render every man uncertain in his enjoyments; not knowing at what time, ſome one of theſe Conſequences might reach him, which would at one blow, ſtrick at the root of all the quiet and ſecure Enjoyments and Poſſeſſions of the Liedges.</p>
               <p>But to return from theſe more remote Conſiderations anent the import of <hi>unlimited Proteſtations</hi> in general, to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Caſe in hand, ſuppoſe that Proteſtations were in every Caſe allowed; yet it ſeems highly unreaſonable, that the ſame ſhould be admitted otherwiſe, than in terms of reſpect to the <hi>Lords,</hi> and in moderation; or that Parties ſhould be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to affix ſuch injurious and reflecting Characters upon their <hi>Deciſions,</hi> as the Petition contains, as if any <hi>Deciſion</hi> of the Lords ſhould be ſo groſly abſurd, <hi>As to violate the Faith of all Contracts, and to wreſt Law to the ruine and defraud of Widows; and not only to encourage indirect Dealings, but to own the deſign of Law to be ſuch, and to deliver a Deciſion that equally impugns Law, Equity and Honesty.</hi> Theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions all contained in the Petition are ſo harſh and rude, that if they were allowed at a Parties pleaſure, it would deprive the Lords of the benefit of that Credit, Reſpect, and Honour, which is due to them by many former Laws, ſeveral times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iterate in every Reign, ſince the Inſtitution of the Colledge of Juſtice; and which were thought neceſſary in the former and preſent Ages, not ſo much for regard to the Perſons of the Judges, as to the Intereſt and Security of the People, that theſe to whom the final determination of all civil Cauſes, in the ordinary Adminiſtration Juſtice was committed, might not be over-awed, by the Influence and Humour of any perſon
<pb facs="tcp:42385:31"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap> until upon legal Tryal, they were Convicted to have <hi>done Wrong or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhoneſty,</hi> as the Law bears</p>
               <p>And as this method is not allowable in any Caſe, ſo for clearing the Injury and Injuſtice thereof in this; the ſame is deſired either to be conſidered, as it is ſtated in the Proceſs above mentioned: Or if any perſon be unwilling to beſtow ſo much labour, let it be conſidered in a more general view, what rational probability can ariſe from the Circumſtances of the Judges and Parties, that they ſhould be guilty of ſuch groſs Iniquity, in prejudice of the Lady <hi>Caſtle-haven?</hi> As the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition proports.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Collingtoun</hi> had no near Intereſt, or contingency by Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or otherwayes, to any perſon on the Bench, or in the State; and that which in all former times has created Fears and Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies of corruption and Iniquity, hath either been perſonal Intereſt with, or by the Party, or Court Influence: On the other hand, the Lady <hi>Castle-haven</hi> wanted not a Relation ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the Bench, or in the State; and particularly ſhe is in that near degree of Conſanguinity with the ſole Secretary of State, now <hi>His Majesties High Commiſſioner,</hi> that in Law ſhe is reckoned in the place of a <hi>Parent</hi> to him: And tho' that Noble perſon is indued with more Integrity, Honour &amp; Juſtice, than in the leaſt to deſign, or countenance the over-awing of the <hi>Bench:</hi> Yet the Lords nether were, nor could be Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that her Intereſt was ſufficiently regarded, and that ſhe did not want a juſt Support and Countenance of her Friends and Relations; withall not above one or two of the Lords were Perſonally known to the King, or could be ſuppoſed to have their Advancement in Places, without the Influence of the <hi>Secretary;</hi> and it would appear, they had very carly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got their gratitude, if they could in ſo few Weeks after their Advancement, be guilty of ſuch groſs Iniquity to the near Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of ſo eminent a Perſon, by whom they were ſo lately Obliged. And tho' they could have forgot their Gratitude, and alſo the <hi>Oath of God</hi> that lay upon them, and all without
<pb facs="tcp:42385:32"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap> they did ſo far neglect their Intereſt, as to Diſoblige a perſon, whoſe Favour might be ſo uſeful, in ſupporting them, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving their farther Intereſt? Beſides, were they Ignorant that there were many envious Beholders, to obſerve their Halting, eſpecially in the beginning of their Adminiſtration: And what was to intice them to all this groſs Iniquity? Let the World but conſider, if the <hi>Deciſion</hi> had run on the other ſide, and that <hi>Collingtoun</hi> had Interpoſed a Proteſtation. What In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence might theſe general conſiderations have obtained in the minds of theſe who are only fit or willing to receive a general view? But the <hi>Deciſion</hi> in this caſe, did carry ſo little preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any byaſs or corruption, that it gave a general ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and nothing could have more reaſonably vindicat the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Integrity and Juſtice of the <hi>Lords</hi> in the eyes of all indifferent Perſons, it being thereby evident, they could not be influenced by any intereſt or by-end; And it is not queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but the great Perſons who have Relation to the Lady will find it their Intereſt and Credit to ſupport the Lords, in deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining according to their Conſciences, and that they will look upon it as a great Honour to them, That during their influence, The Judges of the Land were not overawed or afraid by the Intereſt of any party, to determine according to the Law and their Judgements, as it is recorded of one of the greateſt of our Kings, that the Lords having in his own preſence, Determined Againſt his intereſt, He rejoyced in the Integrity of his Judges, neglecting his loſs.</p>
               <p>And wheras the Petition aſſerts, that <hi>the Ladies Lawyers did redargue all the quibbles of her oppoſites to the Conviction of all Lawyers, who were not blinded with perſonal Concern,</hi> for proving this alſo, there is ſtill the ſame Authority, <hi>The Ladies aſſertion.</hi> And that which ſhe is pleaſed to call <hi>Quibbles,</hi> is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued train of uniform <hi>Deciſions,</hi> in the caſes of clauſes of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſce</hi> to Wives and Children, for the ſpace of above ſixty years, By all which, the Lords have followed one conſtant Rule, <hi>That ſuch Clauſes do not hinder a Husband or Father to uſe a
<pb facs="tcp:42385:32"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                        <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                     </gap> during his Life, albeit theſe ſhould wholly exhauſt the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſce at his Death,</hi> As appears by the Abbreviat of <hi>Deciſions</hi> above mentioned, whereof many more of the like Import could have been produced. And it is ſtrange, that all Lawyers not blinded with perſonal Concern, ſhould be ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of my Ladies Right, ſeing the Lords were ſo unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in a different Opinion, and that their perſonal Intereſt for <hi>Collingtoun,</hi> could not juſtly be ſuſpected. And the Lady, in all the freedom ſhe takes with them doth not brand them with Ignorance, that they did not underſtand her Caſe; nor doth ſhe pretend, that it was not fully and maturely conſidered (the ſame being debated in <hi>Preſentiâ</hi> three intire dayes; and after Informations, another day ſpent in Adviſing) only the Judges were <hi>So prone to Iniquity, that ſurpaſſing the example of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, they practiſed unjuſtice for unjuſtice ſake, without the leaſt bait or allurement to engage them to it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And laſtly all the Iniquity that my Lady Complaines of, Is this, <hi>That Collingtoun ſucceeded to his Fathers Estate, which was relieved by his purchaſs, during the Marriage whereof ſhe Craves the Liferent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It were improper and tedious, to repeate the ſatisfying an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers in this place, which are fully contained in the informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions abovementioned. Only if the Ladie's own Petition be ducly conſidered, it may furniſh no ſmall evidence, that this was no ſuch Iniquity, as is contended. For, 1 The Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion bears That <hi>the deceaſed Collingtoun offered a Joynture of</hi> 3000 <hi>merks yearly, which was all he had, but ſhe did refuſe to accept of that, becauſe thereby the Children of the firſt Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage would altogether want, and therefore ſhe did only take a general clauſe of</hi> Conqueſce <hi>in the termes foreſaid.</hi> Can any thing then be more cleare, than this acknowledgement, that it was the deſigne of Parties, that the Heirs of the Lord <hi>Colling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toun</hi> ſhould ſucceed to his Eſtate of <hi>Collingtoun?</hi> And the very terms of the <hi>Contract,</hi> beſide the preſent acknowledgment bears, that <hi>the Conqueſce during the Marriage, ſhould belong to
<pb facs="tcp:42385:33"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> which failing to</hi> Colingtouns <hi>other Heirs, who are to ſucceed to his other Estate.</hi> So that ſtill it was in proſpect, that the Heirs of the firſt Marriage, ſhould ſucceed to the Eſtate of <hi>Collingtoun,</hi> And that the Lady would not deale ſo with them, as to prejudge them of that Succeſſion, even during her life. This being once acknowledged, how can it be controverted that by the deſigne of the communing and contract, the Defunct was allowed to releive theſe Lands, that his Son might ſucceed? Seing it is imported and acknowledged by every ſtep of the Ladies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, her Summonds, and all the Debate on either hand, That <hi>Collingtouns debt at the time of his Marriage, did exceed the value of his whole Eſtate,</hi> So that it was impoſſible that his Son could ſucceed to any part of the Eſtate, unleſs the debt were payed. And if the Lady had that Juſtice and Affection to the Children, as ſhe expreſſes in her Petition, that ſhe would not hinder them to ſucceed, wherein did this bounty conſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t? Unleſs the Defunct had been allowed to releive his Eſtate, Without which their ſucceſſion thereto, (which the Lady he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf deſigned) was utterly impoſſible; And if any farther evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence were needful, let this be conſidered, that the Lady takes the <hi>Lifrent</hi> of the Houſe and Yeards by her Contract, which ſhe doth poſſeſs, and ſhe refuſes a <hi>Joynture</hi> of 3000 <hi>merks</hi> out of that Eſtate in ſpecial, or by a general obligement, which would have been a Debt affecting the Defuncts Heirs; why was all this done, and a clauſe of Conqueſce accepted in place thereof, if there had been any project for binding up the Defunct from releiving, his own Eſtate? Did ever any Lawyer lay a <hi>clauſe of Conqueſce</hi> in whatſoever terms conceived, in the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance with a <hi>Special Obligement</hi> to a Wife? The one being the <hi>Moſt,</hi> and the other the <hi>Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt</hi> effectual of all obligem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nts.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Collingtoun</hi> did not ſucceed to his Fathers ſmall Eſtate, which the Ladie's Petition owns to be but 3000 <hi>merks</hi> yearly, nor was it releived by his Fathers means, but by his Ladies Portion, which was very conſiderable, and all that his Fa her could contribute for relief thereof, was not valuable; This
<pb facs="tcp:42385:33"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap> Eſtate in <hi>Anno.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which time, his Father had only enjoyed his Sallary, as a Lord of the Seſſion, and a part of his Ladies Joynture, for a few years, which was no Fond to Inrich and Inable him to pay any Conſiderable Debt, after de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of the expences of the Family, and the Education of his Children, upon whom he beſtowed liberally. And it will not be pretended that <hi>Collingtoun</hi> could be lyable for any deed of his Fathers, by miſapplication of Conqueſce or otherwiſe, after he was provided and ſecured to the Eſtate by his contract of Marriage. And if the Defuncts <hi>Conqueſce</hi> were but generally known<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there would not be ground to make ſo great a ſtrugle about the <hi>Liferent</hi> of it. But the true riſe of the Difficulty is in this, that <hi>Collingtoun</hi> never heard or underſtood any thing of the Ladies claime, during his Fathers Life, and thereby was not upon his Guard to provide againſt it, or to keep his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per acquiſition by his Lady, ſeparate from his Fathers Intereſt; but having lived in a perfect and intire Confidence and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with his Father, and ſuffered his Ladie's portion to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, for the payment of his Fathers Debt at his pleaſure, without taking aſſignation to one ſhilling of what was payed, yea without ſo much as mentioning, from whom the Money was received, the difficulty of clearing what was payed by his <hi>own Money,</hi> makes him the more concerned to <hi>Defend,</hi> and the Lady more earneſt to <hi>purſue,</hi> ſhe hoping by the proceſs, to have reached not only the Liferent of her <hi>Husbands Conquest,</hi> but likewayes of this <hi>Collingtouns Portion</hi> with his Lady, which is far from the Kindneſs, and Juſt Inclinations, expreſt in the Ladie's Petition, to have been communed at the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of Marriage, in favours of the Defuncts Heirs and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
